<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2010s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2010s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Philosophers’ songbook #philbitescomp</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/philosophers-songbook-philbitescomp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/philosophers-songbook-philbitescomp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was so inspired by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#search?q=%23philbitescomp&#34;&gt;#philbitescomp&lt;/a&gt; twitter contest that I wrote a short history of philosophy in tweetable fragments of songs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;*Parmenides’ lament:*I guess it will make a change&lt;br&gt;&#xA;when things stop changing&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heracleitus’ blues:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;I cried you the same river&lt;br&gt;&#xA;thrice&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plato’s polka:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;two steps out of the cave&lt;br&gt;&#xA;and look at what you’re doing&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Descartes’ swan song:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;unbidden unwelcome it counts&lt;br&gt;&#xA;yet for a penny I perish&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bishop Berkeley’s soccer fan chant:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Hey Samuel Johnson&lt;br&gt;&#xA;You’re kicking that rock in my mind&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metaphor is my co-pilot: How the literal and metaphorical rely on the same type of knowledge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/metaphor-is-my-co-pilot-how-the-literal-and-metaphorical-rely-on-the-same-type-of-knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/metaphor-is-my-co-pilot-how-the-literal-and-metaphorical-rely-on-the-same-type-of-knowledge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Thanks” to experimental philosophy, we have a bit more evidence confirming, that what many people think about the special &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epistemology&#34; title=&#34;Epistemology&#34;&gt;epistemological&lt;/a&gt; status of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphor&#34; title=&#34;Metaphor&#34;&gt;metaphor&lt;/a&gt; is bunk. We should also note that Gibbs’ and Glucksberg’s teams have been doing a lot of similar research with the same results since the late 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is how &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joshua_Knobe&#34; title=&#34;Joshua Knobe&#34;&gt;Joshua Knobe&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://experimentalphilosophy.typepad.com/experimental_philosophy/2010/08/what-metaphors-mean.html&#34;&gt;Experimental Philosophy&lt;/a&gt; blog summarized a forthcoming paper by Mark Phelan (&lt;a href=&#34;http://pantheon.yale.edu/~mp622/inadequacy.pdf&#34;&gt;http://pantheon.yale.edu/~mp622/inadequacy.pdf&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In short, it looks like it really is pretty impossible to explain what a metaphor means. But that is not because of anything special about metaphors. It is merely a reflection of the fact that we can’t explain what any sentence means.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://experimentalphilosophy.typepad.com/experimental_philosophy/2010/08/what-metaphors-mean.html&#34;&gt;Experimental Philosophy: What Metaphors Mean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Tortoise and the Hare: Analogy for Academia in the Digital World?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/the-tortoise-and-the-hare-analogy-for-academia-in-the-digital-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/the-tortoise-and-the-hare-analogy-for-academia-in-the-digital-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dancohen.org&#34; title=&#34;Dan Cohen&#34;&gt;Dan Cohen&lt;/a&gt; has decided to “&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crowdsourcing&#34; title=&#34;Crowdsourcing&#34;&gt;crowdsource&lt;/a&gt;” (a fascinating blend, by the way) the title of his next book with the following instructions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The title should be a couplet like “The X and the Y” where X can be “Highbrow Humanities” “Elite Academia” “The Ivory Tower” “Deep/High Thought” [insert your idea] and Y can be “Lowbrow Web” “Common Web” “Vernacular Technology/Web” “Public Web” [insert your idea]. so possible titles are “The Highbrow Humanities and the Lowbrow Web” or “The Ivory Tower and the Wild Web” etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Chomsky doesn’t count as a gifted linguist</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/why-chomsky-doesnt-count-as-a-gifted-linguist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/why-chomsky-doesnt-count-as-a-gifted-linguist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Somebody commented on the Language Log saying “of course […] Chomsky was a massively gifted linguist” &lt;a href=&#34;http://j.mp/9Q98Bx&#34;&gt;http://j.mp/9Q98Bx&lt;/a&gt; and for some reason, to use a Czech idiom, the handle of the jar repeatedly used to fetch water just fell off. Meaning, I’ve had enough.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think we should stop thinking of Chomsky as a gifted linguist. He was certainly a gifted mathematician and logician still is a gifted orator and analyst of political discourse (sometimes putting professionals in this area to shame). But I honestly cannot think of a single insight he’s had about how language works as language. His main contribution to the study of language (his only one really) was a description of how certain combinatorial properties of English syntax can be modeled using a particular formal system.  This was a valuable insight but as has been repeatedly documented (e.g. Newmeyer 1986) its runaway success was due to a particular historical context and was later fed by the political prominence of its originator. Unfortunately, everything that followed was predicated on the model being isomorphic with the thing modeled. Meaning all subsequent insights of Chomsky and his followers were confined to refining the model in response to what other people knew about language and not once that I can think of using it to elucidate an actual linguistic phenomenon. (Well, I tell lie here, James MacCawley who worked with GB – and there must have been others – was probably an exception.) Chomsky’s followers who actually continued to have real insights about language – Ross,  Langacker, Lakoff, Fillmore – simply ceased to work within that field – their frustration given voice here by Robin Tolmach Lakoff:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why ideas aren’t enough to solve the Palestine-Israeli conflict</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/why-ideas-arent-enough-to-solve-the-palestine-israeli-conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/why-ideas-arent-enough-to-solve-the-palestine-israeli-conflict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2010-07/23/crowdsource-israeli-palestinian-conflict&#34;&gt;advertising agency is trying to solve a bloody conflict&lt;/a&gt;. This is presumptuous on such as scale that it could be called idiotic. Quoth &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theimpossiblebrief.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.theimpossiblebrief.com&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Rather than ‘out of date’ policies, we need ‘out of the box’ solutions. Let’s show the world that creative minds at their best can inspire even political leaders.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Assuming that there’s an idea out there about resolving this conflict that noone’s ever thought of is nonsense. We should call this assumption that simple ideas can solve difficult problems the “TED Syndrome” (btw: I love TED talks, even if I share &lt;a href=&#34;http://halfanhour.blogspot.com/2010/02/ted-is-political.html&#34;&gt;Stephen Downes’ misgivings&lt;/a&gt; about the TED ‘elite’). Simple solutions to complex problems exist but they are very rare and when we hear about them, we are seldom told the whole story. Generally, it should be safe to assume that a solution should be of proportional complexity to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I write like… a new more sophisticated stripper name?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/i-write-like-a-new-more-sophisticated-stripper-name/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/i-write-like-a-new-more-sophisticated-stripper-name/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Making connections between ourselves and other people no matter how arbitrary, is an incredibly popular communal as well as private activity. The many algorithms for generating one’s stripper, mobster or some other kind of name have graduated from napkins in bars to Facebook apps and now proper quantitative analysis of text samples. But deep down they’re still the same. Is there a space here for hacking? Can we take this natural tendency, take it apart and put it back together again? Use it for good or for ill? I suppose most social engineering is the hacking of propositional frames, but are there explicit hacks of figurative language and thought? It’s certainly powerful enough when you find out that based on the About page here:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What it’s not about so much about</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/what-its-not-about-so-much-about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/what-its-not-about-so-much-about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Enter your email address to subscribe to this blog and receive notifications of new posts by email.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hacking a metaphor in five steps</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/hacking-a-metaphor-in-five-steps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/hacking-a-metaphor-in-five-steps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;preliminaries&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preliminaries&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.&lt;/strong&gt; Before you start &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphor&#34; title=&#34;Metaphor&#34;&gt;metaphor&lt;/a&gt; hacking you must first accept that you don’t have a choice but to speak in some sort of a figurative fashion. Almost nothing worth saying is entirely literal and there are many things whose “literalness” is rooted in metaphor. Look at “I sat in a chair the whole day.” Looks very literal at first glance but it depends on our understanding of a chair as a container (e.g. he was spilling out of his chair) and the day as an object (e.g. she was counting the days, cutting the day short, a long day, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What it’s all About</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/what-its-all-about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/what-its-all-about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphor&#34; title=&#34;Metaphor&#34;&gt;Metaphors&lt;/a&gt; are not just something extra we use when we’re feeling poetic or at a loss for le mot juste, they are all over our minds, texts and conversations. Just like conjunctions, tenses or word. And just like anything else, they can be used for good or ill, on purpose or without conscious regard. Their meanings can be exposed, explored and exorcised. They can be brought from the dead by fresh perspectives or trodden into the ground by frequent use. They may bring us into the very heights of ecstasy or they may pass by unnoticed. They elluminate and obscure, lead and mislead, bring life and death. They can be too constrained or they can taken too far. They can be wrong and they can be right. And they can be hacked.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
