<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2014s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2014s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What language looks like: Dictionary and grammar are to language what standing on one foot is to running</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-language-looks-like-dictionary-and-grammar-are-to-language-what-standing-on-one-foot-is-to-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-language-looks-like-dictionary-and-grammar-are-to-language-what-standing-on-one-foot-is-to-running/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a rather obscure and complex analogy just clicks into place in one’s mind and allows a slightly altered way of thinking that just makes so much sense it hurts. Like putting glasses on in the morning and the world suddenly snapping into shape.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This happened to me this morning when reading the &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychsciencenotes.blogspot.co.uk/2014/10/do-people-really-not-know-what-running.html&#34;&gt;Notes from Two Scientific Psychologists blog&lt;/a&gt; and the post &lt;em&gt;Do people really not know what running looks like?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anthropologists’ metaphorical shenanigans: Or how (not) to research metaphor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/anthropologists-metaphorical-shenanigans-or-how-not-to-research-metaphor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/anthropologists-metaphorical-shenanigans-or-how-not-to-research-metaphor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over on the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://genealogyreligion.net/invisible-disenchantments&#34;&gt;‘Genealogy of Religion’&lt;/a&gt;, Cris Campbell waved a friendly red rag in front of my eyes to make me incensed over exaggerated claims (some) anthropologists make about metaphors. I had expressed some doubts in previous comments but felt that perhaps this particular one deserves its own post.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The book Cris refers to is a collection of essays  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/America-1492-Peoples-Arrival-Columbus/dp/0679743375&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;America in 1492: The World of the Indian Peoples Before the Arrival of Columbus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(1991, ed. Alvin Josephy) which also contains an essay by Joel Sherzer called “A Richness of Voices”.  I don’t have the book but I looked up a few quotes on metaphor from the book.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does it mean when words ‘really’ mean something: Dismiss the Miss</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-does-it-mean-when-words-really-mean-something-dismiss-the-miss/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-does-it-mean-when-words-really-mean-something-dismiss-the-miss/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I tweeted a link to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tes.co.uk/article.aspx?storycode=6427726&#34;&gt;article in TES&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today, I got the following response back:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;@lizzielh is absolutely right. As the title of an as yet unpublished blog post of mine goes: &lt;strong&gt;“Words don’t mean things, people mean things”&lt;/strong&gt;. I even wrote a whole &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/7069654/What_does_it_mean_when_texts_really_mean_something_Types_of_evidence_for_conceptual_patterns_in_discourse&#34;&gt;book chapter on that with the same title as this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, if it had been me writing on the topic, I would have chosen a more judicious title. Such as “The legacy of discrimination behind the humble Miss” or “Past and present inequalities encoded in the simple Miss”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is not a metaphor: Modelling the world through language, thought, science, or action</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-is-not-a-metaphor-modelling-the-world-through-language-thought-science-or-action/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-is-not-a-metaphor-modelling-the-world-through-language-thought-science-or-action/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-role-of-metaphor-in-science-debate-background&#34;&gt;The role of metaphor in science debate (Background)&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Recently, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lse.ac.uk/newsAndMedia/videoAndAudio/channels/publicLecturesAndEvents/player.aspx?id=2289&#34;&gt;LSE podcast an interesting panel on the subject of “Metaphors and Science”&lt;/a&gt;. It featured three speakers talking about the interface between metaphor and various ‘scientific’ disciplines (economics, physics and surgery). Unlike many such occasions, all speakers were actually very knowledgeable and thoughtful on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In particular, I liked Felicity Mellor and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lse.ac.uk/researchAndexpertise/experts/profile.aspx?KeyValue=r.bronk%40lse.ac.uk&#34;&gt;Richard Bronk&lt;/a&gt; who adopted the same perspective that underlies this blog and which I most recently articulated in &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.net/2013/10/pervasiveness-of-oblidging-metaphors-in-thought-and-deed&#34;&gt;writing about obliging metaphors&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imperial.ac.uk/AP/faces/pages/read/Home.jsp?person=f.mellor&amp;amp;_adf.ctrl-state=g30lcwtcs_3&amp;amp;_afrRedirect=1604205418236000&#34;&gt;Felicity Mellor&lt;/a&gt; put it especially eloquently when she said:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linguistics according to Fillmore</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/linguistics-according-to-fillmore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/linguistics-according-to-fillmore/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While people keep banging on about &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2010/08/why-chomsky-doesnt-count-as-a-gifted-linguist/&#34; title=&#34;Why Chomsky doesn’t count as a gifted linguist&#34;&gt;Chomsky&lt;/a&gt; as being the be all and end all of linguistics (I’m looking at you philosophers of language), there have been many linguists who have had a much more substantial impact on how we actually think about language in a way that matters. In my post on why &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2010/08/why-chomsky-doesnt-count-as-a-gifted-linguist/&#34; title=&#34;Why Chomsky doesn’t count as a gifted linguist&#34;&gt;Chomsky is not really a linguist at all&lt;/a&gt; I listed a few.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 things everybody should know about language: Outline of linguistics’ contribution to the liberal arts curriculum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/5-things-everybody-should-know-about-language-outline-of-linguistics-contribution-to-the-liberal-arts-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/5-things-everybody-should-know-about-language-outline-of-linguistics-contribution-to-the-liberal-arts-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;drafty&#34;&gt;Drafty&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This was written in some haste and needs further refinement. Maybe one day that will come. For now, it will be left as it stands.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This post outlines what I think are the key learnings from the output of the research of the field of linguistics that should be reflected in the general curriculum (in as much as any should be). This is in reaction to the recent posts by Mark Liberman suggesting the role and form of grammar analysis in general education. I argue that he is almost entirely wrong in his assumptions as well as in his emphasis. I will outline my arguments against his position at the end of the post. At the beginning I will outline key easily digestible lessons of modern linguistics that should be incorporated into language education at all levels.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
