<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2019s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2019s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>So you think you have a historical analogy? Revisionist history and anthropology reading list</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/so-you-think-you-have-a-historical-analogy-revisionist-history-and-anthropology-reading-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/so-you-think-you-have-a-historical-analogy-revisionist-history-and-anthropology-reading-list/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-this-about&#34;&gt;What is this about&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-badly-were-getting-history&#34;&gt;How badly we’re getting history&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While the world of history and anthropology of the last 30-40 years has completely redrawn the picture of our past, the common perception of the overall shape of history and the development of humanity is still firmly rooted in the view that took hold in the 1800s’ mixture of enlightenment and romanticism.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On this view, we are the pinnacle of development, the logical and inevitable outcome of all that came before us. The development of what is us, the changes in history and culture, can be traced in a straight line from the primitive of the past to the sophisticated of the present. From the savage to the civilized (even if we may eschew these for more polite terms).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turing tests in Chinese rooms: What does it mean for AI to outperform humans</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/turing-tests-in-chinese-rooms-what-does-it-mean-for-ai-to-outperform-humans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/turing-tests-in-chinese-rooms-what-does-it-mean-for-ai-to-outperform-humans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TLDR;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Reports that AI beat humans on certain benchmarks or very specialised tasks don’t mean that AI is actually better at those tasks than any individual human.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;They certainly don’t mean that AI is approaching the task with any of the same understanding of the world people do.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;People actually perform 100% on the tasks when administered individually under ideal conditions (no distraction, typical cognitive development, enough time, etc.) They will start making errors only if we give them too many tasks in too short a time.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This means that just adding more of these results will NOT cumulatively approach general human cognition.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But it may mean that AI can replace people on certain tasks that were previously mistakenly thought to require general human intelligence.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All tests of artificial intelligence suffer from Goodart’s law.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A test more closely resembling an internship or an apprenticeship than a gameshow may be a more effective version of the Imitation Game.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Worries about ‘superintelligence’ are very likely to be irrelevant because they are based on an unproven notion of arbitrary scalability of intelligence and ignore limits on computability.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;reports-of-my-intelligence-have-been-greatly-exaggerated&#34;&gt;Reports of my intelligence have been greatly exaggerated&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, there have been various pronouncements about AI being better than humans at various tasks such as image recognition, speech transcription, or even translation. And that’s not even taking into account bogus winners of the Turing test challenge. To make things worse, there’s always the implication that this is means machine learning is getting closer to human learning and artificial intelligence is only a step away from going general.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fruit loops and metaphors: Metaphors are not about explaining the abstract through concrete but about the dynamic process of negotiated sensemaking</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-through-concrete-but-about-the-dynamic-process-of-negotiated-sensemaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-through-concrete-but-about-the-dynamic-process-of-negotiated-sensemaking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;**Note:**This is a slightly edited version of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/metaphor-hacker/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-through-concrete-but-4e0209dd70b6&#34;&gt;post that first appeared on Medium&lt;/a&gt;. It elaborates and exemplifies examples I gave in the more recent posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/05/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/&#34;&gt;metaphor and explanation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/06/5-kinds-of-understanding-and-metaphors-missing-pieces-in-pedagogical-taxonomies/&#34;&gt;understanding&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the less fortunate consequences of the popularity of the conceptual metaphor paradigm (which is also the one I by and large work with on this blog) is the highlighting of the embodied metaphor at the expenses of others. This gives the impression that metaphors are there to explain more abstract concepts in terms of more concrete ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 books on knowledge and expertise: Reading list for exploring the role of knowledge and deliberate practice in the development of expert performance</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/5-books-on-knowledge-and-expertise-reading-list-for-exploring-the-role-of-knowledge-and-deliberate-practice-in-the-development-of-expert-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/5-books-on-knowledge-and-expertise-reading-list-for-exploring-the-role-of-knowledge-and-deliberate-practice-in-the-development-of-expert-performance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I’ve been exploring the notion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/05/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/&#34;&gt;explanation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/06/5-kinds-of-understanding-and-metaphors-missing-pieces-in-pedagogical-taxonomies/&#34;&gt;understanding&lt;/a&gt;. I was (partly implicitly) relying on the notion of ‘mental representations’ as built through deliberate practice. My plan was to write next about how I think we can reconceptualize deliberate practice in such a way that it draws on a richer conception of ‘mental representations’. But that is turning out to be a much longer project.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, in a recent conversation about teaching practitioners, somebody mentioned reading Kahneman’s ‘Thinking Fast and Slow’ as being relevant to the problem and we discussed maybe starting a reading group. This got me thinking about what should such a reading group have on its reading list.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing as translation and translation as commitment: Why is (academic) writing so hard?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/writing-as-translation-and-translation-as-commitment-why-is-academic-writing-so-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/writing-as-translation-and-translation-as-commitment-why-is-academic-writing-so-hard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This book will perhaps only be understood by those who have themselves already thought the thoughts which are expressed in it—or similar thoughts. It is therefore not a text-book. Its object would be attained if there were one person who read it with understanding and to whom it afforded pleasure.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;(opening sentence of the preface to Tractatus Logico Philosophicus by Lugwig Wittgenstein, 1918)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently been commenting quite a lot on the excellent academic writing blog (which I mostly read for the epistemology) &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.cbs.dk/inframethodology&#34;&gt;Inframethodology&lt;/a&gt; by Thomas Basbøll. Thomas and I disagree on a lot of details but we have a very similar approach to formulating questions about knowledge and its expression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 kinds of understanding and metaphors: Missing pieces in pedagogical taxonomies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/5-kinds-of-understanding-and-metaphors-missing-pieces-in-pedagogical-taxonomies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/5-kinds-of-understanding-and-metaphors-missing-pieces-in-pedagogical-taxonomies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This post outlines 5 levels or types of understanding to help us better to think about the role of &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/05/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/&#34;&gt;metaphor in explanation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Associative understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Place a concept in context without any understanding.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dictionary understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Repeat definitions, give examples, and make basic connections.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inferential understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Make useful inferences based on knowledge about – but without ability to use the understanding in practice. Requires more than just one concept.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instrumental understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Use the understanding as part of work in a field of expertise. Impossible to acquire for an isolated concept.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creative understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Transform understanding of one domain by importing elements from another. Requires instrumental understanding – goes beyond hints and hunches.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/05/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I proposed three uses of metaphor leading to different levels of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explanation is an event, understanding is a process: How (not) to explain anything with metaphor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There are at least 3 uses of metaphor in the educational process: 1. Invitation to enter; 2. An instrument to grasp knowledge with; 3. Catalyst to transform understanding. Many educators assume that 1 is enough but it rarely leads to any useful understanding.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Explanation is a salient part of the educational process to such an extent that it is often allowed to stand for all of it even though it is only one step.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Explanation often helps the person doing the explaining more than the person being explained at.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Metaphors and explanations have been misused by educators from Socrates to Rousseau.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A metaphor can only be successful if the student already has some knowledge of the target domain. Knowledge of the source domain is often less important.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Metaphor only makes sense if it is a part of a process. A process of learning. It doesn’t do much good on its own.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Teachers love explaining things. Students love understanding things. On the rare occasions that the two coincide, the feeling of joy shines like a beacon for the power of explanation. Teachers tell stories of seeing the “lightbulbs come on” in their students’ eyes. Students remember fondly the ecstatic moments of sudden illumination as their teacher’s words suddenly lit up the darkness within them. Thus the myth of teaching as explaining and learning as understanding those explanations was born.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What would make linguistics a better science? Science as a metaphor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/what-would-make-linguistics-a-better-science-science-as-a-metaphor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/what-would-make-linguistics-a-better-science-science-as-a-metaphor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a lightly edited version of a comment posted on Martin Haspelmath’s blog post “&lt;a href=&#34;https://dlc.hypotheses.org/1741&#34;&gt;Against traditional grammar – and for normal science in linguistics&lt;/a&gt;“.  In it he offers a critique of the current linguistic scene as being unclear as to its goals and in need of better definitions. He proposes ‘normal science’ as an alternative:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In many fields of science, comparative research is based on &lt;strong&gt;objective measurements&lt;/strong&gt;, not on categories that are hoped to be universal natural kinds. In linguistics, we can work with objectively defined &lt;strong&gt;comparative concepts&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/1303024&#34;&gt;Haspelmath 2010&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
