<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Narrative vs Ruminative Sense making: The Mind Red in Tooth and Claw</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2023/narrative-vs-ruminative-sense-making-the-mind-red-in-tooth-and-claw/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2023/narrative-vs-ruminative-sense-making-the-mind-red-in-tooth-and-claw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metaphorhacker.net/2023/08/narrative-vs-ruminative-sense-making-the-mind-red-in-tooth-and-claw/#tl-dr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metaphorhacker.net/2023/08/narrative-vs-ruminative-sense-making-the-mind-red-in-tooth-and-claw/#hunting-for-sense-and-cardboard-gazelles-the-limits-of-a-narrative&#34;&gt;Hunting for sense and cardboard gazelles: The limits of a narrative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metaphorhacker.net/2023/08/narrative-vs-ruminative-sense-making-the-mind-red-in-tooth-and-claw/#getting-the-sense-back-in-a-field-of-grass-the-potential-of-the-ruminative-node&#34;&gt;Getting the sense back in a field of grass: The potential of the ruminative node&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metaphorhacker.net/2023/08/narrative-vs-ruminative-sense-making-the-mind-red-in-tooth-and-claw/#mind-red-in-tooth-and-claw-bringing-narratives-and-ruminatives-together-into-a-single-ecosystem&#34;&gt;Mind red in tooth and claw: Bringing narratives and ruminatives together into a single ecosystem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this post, I dissect two key modes of sense-making: narrative and ruminative:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Narrative Sense-Making&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The narrative mode, often our default due to its vivid place in our experiences, unfolds in a linear, guided fashion, much like a predator hunting its prey.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;However, I argue that its reliance on human experience can become a limitation, especially when it cannot draw on pre-existing knowledge. In a way, it narratives are parasitic on our experience.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruminative Sense-Making&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As a counterpoint, I introduce the ruminative mode, drawing inspiration from the grazing and digestion habits of ruminant animals.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This mode encourages us to revisit and ponder over information in a non-linear, iterative manner.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical Examples&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To illustrate this ruminative mode, I present the examples of economist Tyler Cowen and quantum computing researcher Michael Nielsen.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Both these thinkers read in clusters, revisit content, and integrate new insights into their pre-existing knowledge base.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Drawing from these insights, I propose a balanced approach incorporating both modes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving academic writing: Four books to read during #AcWriMo</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2022/improving-academic-writing-four-books-to-read-during-acwrimo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2022/improving-academic-writing-four-books-to-read-during-acwrimo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-acwrimo&#34;&gt;What is #AcWriMo&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;November is the month of writing. There’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Novel_Writing_Month&#34;&gt;NaNoWriMo (National Novel Writing Month)&lt;/a&gt; for writing fiction but also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phd2published.com/acwri-2/acbowrimo/about/&#34;&gt;AcWriMo (Academic Writing Month)&lt;/a&gt; for producing academic writing. The idea behind NaNoWriMo is to make a commitment and finish a piece of writing. This makes more sense for fiction because everyone has that novel inside them and having a month to have a go all out at it is a sensible thing. You may not finish but by the end of the month, you will probably know if you have what it takes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unintentional Pygmalions: 4 questions to ask when checking an artificial entity for sentience and how to think about the answers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2022/unintentional-pygmalions-4-questions-to-ask-when-checking-an-artificial-entity-for-sentience-and-how-to-think-about-the-answers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2022/unintentional-pygmalions-4-questions-to-ask-when-checking-an-artificial-entity-for-sentience-and-how-to-think-about-the-answers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This post has two independent parts:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I ask what would some of the &lt;strong&gt;basic criteria for sentience&lt;/strong&gt; be and how to check for them in a way that would give us a chance to satisfy our need to know.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I explore some of the &lt;strong&gt;dilemmas a fully machine-based sentient entity would have to face&lt;/strong&gt; or rather paradoxes we would have to address.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here are four things, I think it’s worth checking for, each with a relatively simple question or task. They are:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning is a Journey: Consequences of a metaphor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2022/learning-is-a-journey-consequences-of-a-metaphor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2022/learning-is-a-journey-consequences-of-a-metaphor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-to-read-this&#34;&gt;How to read this&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This will take about &lt;strong&gt;18 minutes to read&lt;/strong&gt; (at &lt;a href=&#34;https://digest.bps.org.uk/2019/06/13/most-comprehensive-review-to-date-suggests-the-average-persons-reading-speed-is-slower-than-commonly-thought/&#34;&gt;230 words/min&lt;/a&gt;) but the text is structured to make it easy to &lt;strong&gt;jump around&lt;/strong&gt; and find the key points faster. I tend to go into more detail than most people find necessary.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Two &lt;strong&gt;reasons to read&lt;/strong&gt;:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explore a different perspective&lt;/strong&gt; on some aspects of teaching and learning&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See an illustration&lt;/strong&gt; of a generative metaphor analysis&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;two main sections&lt;/strong&gt; can be read independently&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Metaphor breakdown (12 mins)&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Includes a table summarising key comparisons, this can be read instead of the detailed breakdown&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Overall lessons (5 mins)&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Includes an aside on two modes of education (2 mins) that can be skipped&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There are also &lt;strong&gt;paragraphs on&lt;/strong&gt; (they are not necessary to understand the main point):&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;method of metaphor analysis (1 min) and&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;usefulness of metaphor for learning (1 min)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This can be read &lt;strong&gt;in sequence or in parts&lt;/strong&gt; – the order matters but you can circle around&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This was &lt;strong&gt;initially written&lt;/strong&gt; as part of a discussion about how to best organise learning support but it got out of hand. It should be comprehensible on its own.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 fundamental problems of translating metaphor (or anything else)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2022/3-fundamental-problems-of-translating-metaphor-or-anything-else/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2022/3-fundamental-problems-of-translating-metaphor-or-anything-else/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-hard-is-it-to-translate-metaphor&#34;&gt;How hard is it to translate metaphor?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Metaphor seems like it should be very difficult to translate. But I’d like to argue that what is difficult about translating it is not the metaphor part but rather how it is used. This makes it no different from any other aspect of language. But because it is a rather salient use of language, we can use it to illustrate these general problems of translation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World as a directly meaningful place: A comment on Ecological Psychology and the richness of human experience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/world-as-a-directly-meaningful-place-a-comment-on-ecological-psychology-and-the-richness-of-human-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/world-as-a-directly-meaningful-place-a-comment-on-ecological-psychology-and-the-richness-of-human-experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished reading &lt;a href=&#34;https://psychsciencenotes.blogspot.com/2021/11/is-direct-perception-plausible.html&#34;&gt;Andrew Wilson’s series of blog posts&lt;/a&gt; on the foundation of ‘ecological psychology’ This post started as a comment but it was too long for the comment field (and at 1800 words, that’s not a surprise), so I’m posting it here. It is a bit rough and in places, it expects, that you know what the original posts say. I added some quotes for context but the original posts are still worth a read. But even on its own, I think this post lays out the argument for the need of a more robust psychological account of the human experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>History as weather: A fractal theory of history for Ian Morris, Jared Diamond and CGP Grey</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/history-as-weather-a-fractal-theory-of-history-for-ian-morris-jared-diamond-and-cgp-grey/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/history-as-weather-a-fractal-theory-of-history-for-ian-morris-jared-diamond-and-cgp-grey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This post originally &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/metaphor-hacker/history-as-weather-a-fractal-theory-of-history-for-ian-morris-jared-diamond-and-cgp-grey-45b5503486c5&#34;&gt;appeared on Medium&lt;/a&gt; in 2016. This a very lightly revised version with new formatting for &lt;a href=&#34;https://metaphorhacker.net/2021/01/the-nonsense-of-style-academic-writing-should-be-scrupulous-not-stylish/&#34;&gt;ease of readability&lt;/a&gt;. It preceded the post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://metaphorhacker.net/2019/09/so-you-think-you-have-a-historical-analogy-revisionist-history-and-anthropology-reading-list/&#34;&gt;historical revisionism&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://metaphorhacker.net/2020/02/its-not-personal-its-family/&#34;&gt;anthropology of family&lt;/a&gt; but it tackles and elaborates on some of the same themes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;outline-of-the-argument&#34;&gt;Outline of the argument&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History is often accused of not being sufficiently scientific&lt;/strong&gt;. To remedy this people try to come up with all sorts of theories of history that try to look like science. They come up with some measurable variable (e.g. availability of domesticable species as Jared Diamond did or energy output as Ian Morris did or size of population, advancement of technology, size of armies, etc. as many others do). This, they hope, explains the past and predicts the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why I am a feminist: A reading list</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/why-i-am-a-feminist-a-reading-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/why-i-am-a-feminist-a-reading-list/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I became a feminist because a woman once told me not to be an idiot and I decided that it was good advice. That was in 1998. But I was all ready to be a feminist long before that, so it really just took a small push to get me over the hump. I was always surrounded by strong women who outshone the men around them, read books as a boy with girls holding their own, later on had women friends who I could respect and like more than most of my male friends.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nonsense of style: Academic writing should be scrupulous not stylish</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/the-nonsense-of-style-academic-writing-should-be-scrupulous-not-stylish/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/the-nonsense-of-style-academic-writing-should-be-scrupulous-not-stylish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-with-writing-advice&#34;&gt;The problem with writing advice&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The problem with the likes of Steven Pinker and Helen Sword is that they like their own writing way too much. But I don’t. Like their writing, that is. [1] I want to get some information from them and I want to get examples and counterexamples for the points they make. I want them to get to the point. I am not reading them for enjoyment, that’s what fiction is for. I am reading them to learn what they have to say and I have to wade through a morass of stories, pointless metaphors, geysers of words. They are aiming for eloquence but effluence would be a better term for what their reader gets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metaphors and freedom: On Tolkien’s notion of allegory vs applicability</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/metaphors-and-freedom-on-tolkiens-notion-of-allegory-vs-applicability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2021/metaphors-and-freedom-on-tolkiens-notion-of-allegory-vs-applicability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On rereading Tolkien’s Lord of the Rings, I was struck by this passage in his foreword to the second edition:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I cordially dislike allegory in all its manifestations, and always have done so since I grew old and wary enough to detect its presence. I much prefer history, true or feigned, with its varied applicability to the thought and experience of readers. I think that many confuse ‘applicability’ with ‘allegory’; but the one resides in the freedom of the reader, and the other in the purposed domination of the author. &lt;a href=&#34;http://ae-lib.org.ua/texts-c/tolkien__the_lord_of_the_rings_1__en.htm#00&#34;&gt;http://ae-lib.org.ua/texts-c/tolkien__the_lord_of_the_rings_1__en.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No back row, no corridor: Metaphors for online teaching and learning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/no-back-row-no-corridor-metaphors-for-online-teaching-and-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/no-back-row-no-corridor-metaphors-for-online-teaching-and-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;publication-note&#34;&gt;Publication note&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An earlier version of this was published in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://staff.admin.ox.ac.uk/oxford-magazine&#34;&gt;Oxford Magazine&lt;/a&gt; No 422.  This post expands certain sections based on questions and feedback I received following the first publication of the piece. It is also available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/metaphor-hacker/no-back-row-no-corridor-metaphors-for-online-teaching-and-learning-9628f164fc37?source=friends_link&amp;amp;sk=27f6f0666a88d9951c5d16a28d0e00e7&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-state-of-digital-dislocation&#34;&gt;The state of digital dislocation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The current state of digital dislocation is forcing us to reevaluate what is the essence of teaching and learning. The “grammar of schooling” [1] has been taken away from us and we are forced to learn a new dialect by immersion with just a few phrasebooks, hastily pulled off the shelf, to guide us. Digital teaching is still teaching but it is teaching with an accent, one where we’re still trying to acquire enough fluency and idiomaticity to feel completely at home. When we add to it the culture shock of being in a new situation without any of the familiar cues, sights, sounds and smells of our native environment, it is not surprising that many people are feeling stressed and long for a swift return to “normal”. But it is also no surprise that many others are examining the current situation and finding the new land to be one of endless opportunity and thinking of establishing a permanent residence or at least buying a holiday home.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving Events Online Part 1: Challenges: Why are not more events taking place online?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/moving-events-online-part-1-challenges-why-are-not-more-events-taking-place-onli/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/moving-events-online-part-1-challenges-why-are-not-more-events-taking-place-onli/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is Part 1 of a three-part series. Table of contents:&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-platforms-strategies-and-challenges-97464cdc0f2a?sk=9e4809ee02ae5d51c7538f82abcc29b0&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-1-challenges-why-are-not-more-events-taking-place-online-a1b94533649c?sk=cd797ca3ef7c092c2a2bbaafcff09e4c&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-2-strategies-what-can-we-learn-from-successful-online-events-8ae2dbf40703?sk=632297047eef8329e3b5d74db3cc832d&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2: Strategies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-3-platforms-what-technologies-and-solutions-are-available-fd8e2b05b7f0?sk=1f407def5e8e509cdcb7f3272fb59c07&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3: Platforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*JVT0dO-OO1Vv1h3V&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I organised my first video lecture in 2002 when I was teaching in Glasgow and wanted students to get access to experts from London and Prague. It required a dedicated room and a technician on both ends, yet it seemed that an explosion of online teaching was just around the corner. But when I started a public lecture webinar series in 2010, online presentations were still a rarity. Now, webinars and virtual meetings are commonplace but we’re still not seeing a lot of entire events moving online. Even during the time of global lockdown and mass event cancelations, most events are simply cancelled even as teaching, meetings and music concerts move online. Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving Events Online Part 2: Strategies: What can we learn from successful online events?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/moving-events-online-part-2-strategies-what-can-we-learn-from-successful-online/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/moving-events-online-part-2-strategies-what-can-we-learn-from-successful-online/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is Part 2 of a three-part series. Table of contents:&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-platforms-strategies-and-challenges-97464cdc0f2a?sk=9e4809ee02ae5d51c7538f82abcc29b0&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-1-challenges-why-are-not-more-events-taking-place-online-a1b94533649c?sk=cd797ca3ef7c092c2a2bbaafcff09e4c&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-2-strategies-what-can-we-learn-from-successful-online-events-8ae2dbf40703?sk=632297047eef8329e3b5d74db3cc832d&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2: Strategies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-3-platforms-what-technologies-and-solutions-are-available-fd8e2b05b7f0?sk=1f407def5e8e509cdcb7f3272fb59c07&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3: Platforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*jkZW6RCd1Qt_qQSW&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Fully online events are not very common but they exist. Many people have written about some of their experiences that we can learn from. Being more aware of the affordance mismatch between online and physical events can help us make the most of these tips and augment them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;tips-for-organisers&#34;&gt;Tips for organisers&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;initial-considerations&#34;&gt;Initial considerations&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think about the format of the event. Does it have to be just a day or two or can you split a day into a week or two worth of sessions? A more concentrated event can develop more of a feel of unity but may be more intensive to organise and harder to attend for people who join from their place of work.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think about whether you want the event to be synchronous or asynchronous. Synchronous events put much lower demands on presenters and will also have more engagement. People are more likely to attend an hour-long live event than watch the same length video recording. Successful asynchronous events require more intensive moderation with a time commitment for organisers that may span weeks.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think about the formats of the sessions. Do you need to replicate exactly the same formats as in an in-person session? Can you take advantage of the online format? Some conferences offer a Twitter chat as a format. You could also adopt a text interview or panel similar to AMA on Reddit or a moderated online chat. Collaborative document editing such as a Wikipedia editathon or an online documentation sprint are also an option.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think about the virtual space. Do you just want to have a traditional website with lists of links or something that gives the impression of being in space. 3D virtual spaces like Second Life gave people more of a sense of space but they excluded those who found them difficult to navigate. In general, people have good shared mental models of a website and the benefits of a 3D emulation of the physical space are not certain. On the other hand, giving some thought to what should be visually placed together on the website can help make up for the lack of the most natural affordances of space.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think about the medium and modality. Encourage presenters and participants to turn on videos and to attend from spaces that support that. But also encourage people to upload photos (or integrate with LinkedIn) to make the virtual space more personal and add more visual cues to the space.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think about the amount of written text on the event website. Do participants arrive to what looks like a website or something that naturally suggests things happening. Don’t waste space with welcome messages or long descriptions. Even a welcome video just gets in the way. The first thing participants arriving to a website of a live online event should see is where to go next, how to join what is happening.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think about having a chat channel that is constantly monitored by event organisers. Making the chat public is another possibility to enable others to learn from previous questions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;communication-and-presentation&#34;&gt;Communication and presentation&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Have a central repository of information about the event with details of how to connect front and centre and promote that. Don’t rely on emails with links.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Have a status board on the front of the event website with what sessions are happening right now and what is coming next. Don’t rely on the schedule with links to sessions. Maybe even have a counter of how many people are in sessions at the moment and have a ticker of questions or chat being asked.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Allow participants to sign up for individual sessions and make sure that they can integrate it into their calendar and get individual email reminders. Just having a schedule they can click on doesn’t take into account their need to integrate the event into their life.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think about having stable links to virtual rooms and give the rooms a name. There is some potential for confusion as people join the wrong session or come in for a session that’s still running but it will replicate some of the serendipity of a live event. Having unique links for each session has some technical advantages because presenters and facilitators can prepare ahead of time but if you build enough breaks between sessions, this could alleviate the problem.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Let participants promote the event in ways that is natural. Having an event hashtag for Twitter and Instagram is easy. But you should also have collateral to share. Have images that people can put on Instagram, offer a tweet of the day prize for the weeks running up to the conference. Reward blogging about the event, etc. You should also take the time and promote participants and presenters. Have a featured section on the website where you profile a scheduled talk every day or have event attendee write a short blog post about sessions they’re planning to attend and why.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sessions&#34;&gt;Sessions&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Each live session needs to have 2 roles for success. A session moderator and session technical support.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The moderator (chair) introduces the presenter, keeps track of time and then moderates the discussion. If there is a chat functionality, they should monitor and answer routine questions and collate questions for asking later. They could also interrupt the presenter if the question seems urgent. This could be a role taken on by the presenter themselves as it often is in live events but not all presenters will have the ability to monitor all aspects of the session. It is particularly useful to have a second person available when questions come in via text who can read them out.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The technical support person helps troubleshoot issues with microphones, screen sharing, or other technical use of the platform. They may also be responsible for starting the session (depending on the platform). The moderator can play this role if technically adept, or one technical support person can look after multiple sessions. But event organisers should expect the need for more technical support for online events. Often, these people will have nothing to do but their presence makes much more difference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Panels and round tables work well in the virtual format and can be successful when moderated well. This does work best when all panelists’ videos are visible. Most platforms also have features for creating break out groups which may be an option for replicating the unconference format.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lightning talks are becoming increasingly popular at events and these would be very easy to replicate online (although they don’t seem to be). A number of presenters simply pass screensharing and microphone control over and present short (3–7 min) talks. This can be moderated easily and be augmented by the presence of a text chat channel.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not all sessions have to be in the form of a live presentation to an audience. Here are four suggestions for alternatives:&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Having an AMA (Ask me anything) style Q&amp;amp;A that was popularised by Reddit can be a powerful engagement. A presenter (usually somebody with a unique experience or point of view) can be available for a specified period of time (anywhere from an hour to week) to answer questions that people type in. This works best if the person is sufficiently known or the size of the audience is large to ensure questions are asked. The organisers may also substitute questions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Group chat known from platforms such as Slack or Teams could replicate the experience of a live panel. An example of how this works is a moderated Slack discussion published by the website FiveThirtyEight. This could be organised live and / or published afterwards. But immediacy is important. This format requires a panel of people who are sufficiently acquainted with this form of communication and a competent moderator.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Twitter chat where participants follow a topic (using a hashtag) for a specified amount of time (usually an hour) has become an established group communication medium. Here all of the event’s virtual attendees can participate. These work best when moderated and require that participants use Twitter. By its nature, this happens in the public eye but could be replicated in a closed platform by open chat.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Editathon is another medium where a group works together on creating or editing a document on a single topic. These were popularised by Wikipedia but can be implemented easily using a shared Google Doc. Editathons can last anywhere from an hour to a week (when they are longer, they are also sometimes called book sprints but these are usually in person) and work best when people commit to them and have some system of communication and moderation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;social-environment&#34;&gt;Social environment&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Giving the online event a sense of cohesion (time and place) is perhaps the most difficult aspect to replicate. This is where the Second Life platform offered the most potential because it was possible to see representations of other people in the same space. But virtual environments with avatars are not as easy to navigate for everyone as a website so will ultimately reduce participation. Here are some suggestions based on what has been tried:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving Events Online Part 3: Platforms: What technologies and solutions are available?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/moving-events-online-part-3-platforms-what-technologies-and-solutions-are-availa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/moving-events-online-part-3-platforms-what-technologies-and-solutions-are-availa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is Part 3 of a three-part series. Table of contents:&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-platforms-strategies-and-challenges-97464cdc0f2a?sk=9e4809ee02ae5d51c7538f82abcc29b0&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-1-challenges-why-are-not-more-events-taking-place-online-a1b94533649c?sk=cd797ca3ef7c092c2a2bbaafcff09e4c&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-2-strategies-what-can-we-learn-from-successful-online-events-8ae2dbf40703?sk=632297047eef8329e3b5d74db3cc832d&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2: Strategies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-3-platforms-what-technologies-and-solutions-are-available-fd8e2b05b7f0?sk=1f407def5e8e509cdcb7f3272fb59c07&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3: Platforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*8J1VMeAj7_jL_oV-&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@gabrielbenois?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Gabriel Benois&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are essentially two kinds of platforms that can be considered for running live synchronous events.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Point-to-point platforms&lt;/strong&gt; that are used primarily for organising one off webinars or meetings (such as Zoom, GoToWebinar, Big Blue Button and more)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrated event platforms&lt;/strong&gt; that facilitate the entire event from registration to communication to connecting participants live.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;affordances-of-point-to-point-platforms&#34;&gt;Affordances of Point-to-point platforms&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The point-to-point platforms are well-established and well-understood. Most people in the education or corporate sectors have either participated in an online meeting run on one of these platforms or at least have some mental model of what it is about. At the very least, they can fall back on analogies, “it’s like a Skype call or Facetime”. Many more people will have also participated in webinars or watched recordings or them which is what these platforms are for.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving events online: Platforms, strategies and challenges</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/moving-events-online-platforms-strategies-and-challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/moving-events-online-platforms-strategies-and-challenges/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*gJOj6sJgKXV_4Q2s&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@xteemu?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Teemu Paananen&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the introduction to a three-part series. Table of contents:&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-platforms-strategies-and-challenges-97464cdc0f2a?sk=9e4809ee02ae5d51c7538f82abcc29b0&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-1-challenges-why-are-not-more-events-taking-place-online-a1b94533649c?sk=cd797ca3ef7c092c2a2bbaafcff09e4c&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-2-strategies-what-can-we-learn-from-successful-online-events-8ae2dbf40703?sk=632297047eef8329e3b5d74db3cc832d&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2: Strategies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/techczech/moving-events-online-part-3-platforms-what-technologies-and-solutions-are-available-fd8e2b05b7f0?sk=1f407def5e8e509cdcb7f3272fb59c07&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3: Platforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We are seeing a flood of event cancellations in response to the global threat of COVID-19. This has triggered renewed interest in organising virtual conferences and generally moving face-to-face events into the virtual space. These discussions are not new. The environmental impact of the many thousands of events taking place around the world has had people question whether they should try to run more events online. But neither this nor the significant cost of attending these events has led to a significant reduction of conference travel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It’s not personal, it’s family: Kin, strangers, guests, and the complexity of social obligation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/its-not-personal-its-family-kin-strangers-guests-and-the-complexity-of-social-obligation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/its-not-personal-its-family-kin-strangers-guests-and-the-complexity-of-social-obligation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;brooks-on-the-alternatives-to-nuclear-family&#34;&gt;Brooks on the alternatives to nuclear family&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https:marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2020/02/the-importance-of-family-structure-was-the-nuclear-family-a-mistake.html&#34;&gt;Tyler Cowen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;His portrayal of the current social environment is well worth reading and rereading:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“If you want to summarize the changes in family structure over the past century, the truest thing to say is this: We’ve made life freer for individuals and more unstable for families. We’ve made life better for adults but worse for children. We’ve moved from big, interconnected, and extended families, which helped protect the most vulnerable people in society from the shocks of life, to smaller, detached nuclear families (a married couple and their children), which give the most privileged people in society room to maximize their talents and expand their options.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to actually write a sentence: The building blocks of written language</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/how-to-actually-write-a-sentence-the-building-blocks-of-written-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/how-to-actually-write-a-sentence-the-building-blocks-of-written-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, Thomas Basbøll followed up his excellent post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.cbs.dk/inframethodology/?p=2676&#34;&gt;how to write a paragraph&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“it is substantially more difficult to explain what one does when one writes a sentence than it is to explain what one does when one composes a paragraph.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it is much more difficult to talk about the mechanics of writing the sentence because we generally want to forget we are composing a sentence, whereas we want to focus on the fact we are composing a paragraph. In this, writing a sentence is much like riding a bicycle. You cannot really do it successfully while attending to every aspect of the process. Basbøll’s metaphor here is very apt:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potemkin wisdoms, phronesis and Pixar: How wise sayings protect us from meaning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/potemkin-wisdoms-phronesis-and-pixar-how-wise-sayings-protect-us-from-meaning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/potemkin-wisdoms-phronesis-and-pixar-how-wise-sayings-protect-us-from-meaning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an exploration of the difference between wisdom and practical wisdom (phronesis) triggered by this quote from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v%3Dk2h2lvhzMDc&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;ust=1579646399857000&#34;&gt;a talk by Ed Catmull&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Once one can articulate an important idea into a concise statement, then one can use this statement, and not have to have the fear of changing behavior.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The main lesson is: if we confuse understanding with repeating its summary, we hollow out its meaning and can no longer rely on it to inform what we do.  &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictions for the next decade: Hopes, dreams and reality checks: Part 6 of Tech That Reshaped…</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/predictions-for-the-next-decade-hopes-dreams-and-reality-checks-part-6-of-tech-t/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/predictions-for-the-next-decade-hopes-dreams-and-reality-checks-part-6-of-tech-t/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;predictions-for-the-next-decade-hopes-dreams-and-reality-checks-part-6-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-lastdecade&#34;&gt;Predictions for the next decade: Hopes, dreams and reality checks: Part 6 of Tech That Reshaped our Lives in the Last Decade&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is part 6 of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;6-part series&lt;/a&gt;. Read &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;Part 1 for Background&lt;/a&gt;. Go back to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/media-and-content-consumption-trends-of-the-2010s-part-4-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-81a170a3bfd3?source=friends_link&amp;amp;sk=a61e7419d6790613ff96989a785f3afe&#34;&gt;Part 5 on Hype Bubble of the 2010s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*ay5L_2kN1U-zDwvF&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@drew_beamer?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Drew Beamer&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the next decade, the tech in our lives will be faster, cheaper, more energy-efficient, better connected, and smarter than it is today. But all these advances are going to be much more boring than we imagine. The world of tech will look more the same than different. I predict:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardware Trends of the 2010s: Part 2 of Tech That Reshaped our Lives in the Last Decade</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/hardware-trends-of-the-2010s-part-2-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/hardware-trends-of-the-2010s-part-2-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part 2 of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;6-part series&lt;/a&gt;. Read &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;Part 1 for Background&lt;/a&gt;. Go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/software-trends-of-the-2010s-part-3-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last-decade-3b824a6bb6e1?sk=a52f0c324777b424acb5de55ebbfd52c&#34;&gt;Part 3 on Software trends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to hardware, the last decade has brought some subtle but important changes to the sort of hardware we buy and use.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*Egj3RF6zZ4-N6Euy&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@alexkixa?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Alexandre Debiève&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;large-screen-phones&#34;&gt;Large-screen phones&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Samsung introduced the first &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samsung_Galaxy_Note_series&#34;&gt;Galaxy Note in 2011&lt;/a&gt;, everybody thought they were crazy because the 5.3 inch screen looked massive. People even felt the need to invent a new term for this, a ‘phablet’. When I saw friend hold her Note to her ear, it looked so strange I had to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/p/Lq3SqpxKpQ/&#34;&gt;take a picture&lt;/a&gt;. When I look at it now, it looks perfectly normal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Media and content consumption trends of the 2010s: Part 4 of Tech That Reshaped our Lives in the…</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/media-and-content-consumption-trends-of-the-2010s-part-4-of-tech-that-reshaped-o/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/media-and-content-consumption-trends-of-the-2010s-part-4-of-tech-that-reshaped-o/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;media-and-content-consumption-trends-of-the-2010s-part-4-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-lastdecade&#34;&gt;Media and content consumption trends of the 2010s: Part 4 of Tech That Reshaped our Lives in the Last Decade&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is part 4 of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;6-part series&lt;/a&gt;. Read &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;Part 1 for Background&lt;/a&gt;. Go back to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/software-trends-of-the-2010s-part-3-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last-decade-3b824a6bb6e1?sk=a52f0c324777b424acb5de55ebbfd52c&#34;&gt;Part 3 on Software trends&lt;/a&gt;. Go next to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/the-hype-bubbles-of-the-2010s-part-5-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last-decade-2e88c8ffb928?sk=7b4a44a1bbd3b523825c4c8a331753ab&#34;&gt;Part 5 on Hype bubbles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The last decade also brought radical changes to the way we consume content. It even made the words ‘consume content’ make sense because it brought together watching TV, listening to music and reading books into the same category.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Trends of the 2010s: Part 3 of Tech That Reshaped our Lives in the Last Decade</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/software-trends-of-the-2010s-part-3-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/software-trends-of-the-2010s-part-3-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part 3 of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;6-part series&lt;/a&gt;. Read &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;Part 1 for Background&lt;/a&gt;. Go back to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/hardware-trends-of-the-2010s-part-2-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last-decade-15946e2c9cee?source=friends_link&amp;amp;sk=5b6762eb473e364ca7c959387c106ae4&#34;&gt;Part 2 on Hardware trends&lt;/a&gt;. Go forward to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/media-and-content-consumption-trends-of-the-2010s-part-4-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-81a170a3bfd3?sk=a61e7419d6790613ff96989a785f3afe&#34;&gt;Part 4 on Media consumption trends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This list is (with one exception) not about individual products but about trends and categories.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*26yR9Kh5kzjKEW3g&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@hishahadat?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Shahadat Rahman&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;dropbox-and-cloud-storage-andsync&#34;&gt;Dropbox and cloud storage and sync&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For me, the first decade of the century was characterised by the USB stick. I always carried a few with me, usually around my neck. The USB drive replaced the previously ubiquitous floppy disk which was the data-transfer medium of the 1990s (even if they lost their floppiness). And while USB sticks are still extremely common and useful, they have been replaced in my life by cloud storage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The hype bubbles of the 2010s: Part 5 of Tech That Reshaped our Lives in the Last Decade</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/the-hype-bubbles-of-the-2010s-part-5-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2020/the-hype-bubbles-of-the-2010s-part-5-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part 5 of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;6-part series&lt;/a&gt;. Read &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/technology-trends-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-2010s-10-years-in-10-000-words-f9be9dfdd22a&#34;&gt;Part 1 for Background&lt;/a&gt;. Go back to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/software-trends-of-the-2010s-part-3-of-tech-that-reshaped-our-lives-in-the-last-decade-3b824a6bb6e1?sk=a52f0c324777b424acb5de55ebbfd52c&#34;&gt;Part 4 on Media consumption trends&lt;/a&gt;. Next: &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@techczech/predictions-for-the-next-decade-hopes-dreams-and-reality-checks-part-6-of-tech-that-reshaped-b2688e0049d4?source=friends_link&amp;amp;sk=bf1df937242483605917ebd9e2495e69&#34;&gt;Predictions for the 2020s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*JzIhoSsKcFgJQVhs&#34; alt=&#34;“”&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@lanju_fotografie?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Lanju Fotografie&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With reflections on the end of any period, there come not only summaries of the greatest successes but also the flops and failures. And the top of this decade proved no exception. The Verge lists &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theverge.com/2019/12/20/21029499/decade-fails-flops-tech-science-culture-apple-google-data-kickstarter-2010-2019&#34;&gt;84 biggest flops&lt;/a&gt; across tech and Audrey Watters came up with &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackeducation.com/2019/12/31/what-a-shitshow&#34;&gt;100 debacles for ed tech&lt;/a&gt; alone. While such schadenfreude may be entertaining or even occasionally edifying, that is not my purpose here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>So you think you have a historical analogy? Revisionist history and anthropology reading list</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/so-you-think-you-have-a-historical-analogy-revisionist-history-and-anthropology-reading-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/so-you-think-you-have-a-historical-analogy-revisionist-history-and-anthropology-reading-list/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-this-about&#34;&gt;What is this about&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-badly-were-getting-history&#34;&gt;How badly we’re getting history&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While the world of history and anthropology of the last 30-40 years has completely redrawn the picture of our past, the common perception of the overall shape of history and the development of humanity is still firmly rooted in the view that took hold in the 1800s’ mixture of enlightenment and romanticism.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On this view, we are the pinnacle of development, the logical and inevitable outcome of all that came before us. The development of what is us, the changes in history and culture, can be traced in a straight line from the primitive of the past to the sophisticated of the present. From the savage to the civilized (even if we may eschew these for more polite terms).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turing tests in Chinese rooms: What does it mean for AI to outperform humans</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/turing-tests-in-chinese-rooms-what-does-it-mean-for-ai-to-outperform-humans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/turing-tests-in-chinese-rooms-what-does-it-mean-for-ai-to-outperform-humans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TLDR;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Reports that AI beat humans on certain benchmarks or very specialised tasks don’t mean that AI is actually better at those tasks than any individual human.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;They certainly don’t mean that AI is approaching the task with any of the same understanding of the world people do.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;People actually perform 100% on the tasks when administered individually under ideal conditions (no distraction, typical cognitive development, enough time, etc.) They will start making errors only if we give them too many tasks in too short a time.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This means that just adding more of these results will NOT cumulatively approach general human cognition.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But it may mean that AI can replace people on certain tasks that were previously mistakenly thought to require general human intelligence.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All tests of artificial intelligence suffer from Goodart’s law.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A test more closely resembling an internship or an apprenticeship than a gameshow may be a more effective version of the Imitation Game.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Worries about ‘superintelligence’ are very likely to be irrelevant because they are based on an unproven notion of arbitrary scalability of intelligence and ignore limits on computability.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;reports-of-my-intelligence-have-been-greatly-exaggerated&#34;&gt;Reports of my intelligence have been greatly exaggerated&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, there have been various pronouncements about AI being better than humans at various tasks such as image recognition, speech transcription, or even translation. And that’s not even taking into account bogus winners of the Turing test challenge. To make things worse, there’s always the implication that this is means machine learning is getting closer to human learning and artificial intelligence is only a step away from going general.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fruit loops and metaphors: Metaphors are not about explaining the abstract through concrete but about the dynamic process of negotiated sensemaking</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-through-concrete-but-about-the-dynamic-process-of-negotiated-sensemaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-through-concrete-but-about-the-dynamic-process-of-negotiated-sensemaking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;**Note:**This is a slightly edited version of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/metaphor-hacker/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-through-concrete-but-4e0209dd70b6&#34;&gt;post that first appeared on Medium&lt;/a&gt;. It elaborates and exemplifies examples I gave in the more recent posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/05/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/&#34;&gt;metaphor and explanation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/06/5-kinds-of-understanding-and-metaphors-missing-pieces-in-pedagogical-taxonomies/&#34;&gt;understanding&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the less fortunate consequences of the popularity of the conceptual metaphor paradigm (which is also the one I by and large work with on this blog) is the highlighting of the embodied metaphor at the expenses of others. This gives the impression that metaphors are there to explain more abstract concepts in terms of more concrete ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 books on knowledge and expertise: Reading list for exploring the role of knowledge and deliberate practice in the development of expert performance</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/5-books-on-knowledge-and-expertise-reading-list-for-exploring-the-role-of-knowledge-and-deliberate-practice-in-the-development-of-expert-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/5-books-on-knowledge-and-expertise-reading-list-for-exploring-the-role-of-knowledge-and-deliberate-practice-in-the-development-of-expert-performance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I’ve been exploring the notion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/05/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/&#34;&gt;explanation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/06/5-kinds-of-understanding-and-metaphors-missing-pieces-in-pedagogical-taxonomies/&#34;&gt;understanding&lt;/a&gt;. I was (partly implicitly) relying on the notion of ‘mental representations’ as built through deliberate practice. My plan was to write next about how I think we can reconceptualize deliberate practice in such a way that it draws on a richer conception of ‘mental representations’. But that is turning out to be a much longer project.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, in a recent conversation about teaching practitioners, somebody mentioned reading Kahneman’s ‘Thinking Fast and Slow’ as being relevant to the problem and we discussed maybe starting a reading group. This got me thinking about what should such a reading group have on its reading list.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing as translation and translation as commitment: Why is (academic) writing so hard?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/writing-as-translation-and-translation-as-commitment-why-is-academic-writing-so-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/writing-as-translation-and-translation-as-commitment-why-is-academic-writing-so-hard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This book will perhaps only be understood by those who have themselves already thought the thoughts which are expressed in it—or similar thoughts. It is therefore not a text-book. Its object would be attained if there were one person who read it with understanding and to whom it afforded pleasure.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;(opening sentence of the preface to Tractatus Logico Philosophicus by Lugwig Wittgenstein, 1918)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently been commenting quite a lot on the excellent academic writing blog (which I mostly read for the epistemology) &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.cbs.dk/inframethodology&#34;&gt;Inframethodology&lt;/a&gt; by Thomas Basbøll. Thomas and I disagree on a lot of details but we have a very similar approach to formulating questions about knowledge and its expression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 kinds of understanding and metaphors: Missing pieces in pedagogical taxonomies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/5-kinds-of-understanding-and-metaphors-missing-pieces-in-pedagogical-taxonomies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/5-kinds-of-understanding-and-metaphors-missing-pieces-in-pedagogical-taxonomies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This post outlines 5 levels or types of understanding to help us better to think about the role of &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/05/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/&#34;&gt;metaphor in explanation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Associative understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Place a concept in context without any understanding.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dictionary understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Repeat definitions, give examples, and make basic connections.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inferential understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Make useful inferences based on knowledge about – but without ability to use the understanding in practice. Requires more than just one concept.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instrumental understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Use the understanding as part of work in a field of expertise. Impossible to acquire for an isolated concept.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creative understanding:&lt;/strong&gt; Transform understanding of one domain by importing elements from another. Requires instrumental understanding – goes beyond hints and hunches.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2019/05/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I proposed three uses of metaphor leading to different levels of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explanation is an event, understanding is a process: How (not) to explain anything with metaphor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/explanation-is-an-event-understanding-is-a-process-how-not-to-explain-anything-with-metaphor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There are at least 3 uses of metaphor in the educational process: 1. Invitation to enter; 2. An instrument to grasp knowledge with; 3. Catalyst to transform understanding. Many educators assume that 1 is enough but it rarely leads to any useful understanding.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Explanation is a salient part of the educational process to such an extent that it is often allowed to stand for all of it even though it is only one step.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Explanation often helps the person doing the explaining more than the person being explained at.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Metaphors and explanations have been misused by educators from Socrates to Rousseau.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A metaphor can only be successful if the student already has some knowledge of the target domain. Knowledge of the source domain is often less important.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Metaphor only makes sense if it is a part of a process. A process of learning. It doesn’t do much good on its own.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Teachers love explaining things. Students love understanding things. On the rare occasions that the two coincide, the feeling of joy shines like a beacon for the power of explanation. Teachers tell stories of seeing the “lightbulbs come on” in their students’ eyes. Students remember fondly the ecstatic moments of sudden illumination as their teacher’s words suddenly lit up the darkness within them. Thus the myth of teaching as explaining and learning as understanding those explanations was born.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What would make linguistics a better science? Science as a metaphor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/what-would-make-linguistics-a-better-science-science-as-a-metaphor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2019/what-would-make-linguistics-a-better-science-science-as-a-metaphor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a lightly edited version of a comment posted on Martin Haspelmath’s blog post “&lt;a href=&#34;https://dlc.hypotheses.org/1741&#34;&gt;Against traditional grammar – and for normal science in linguistics&lt;/a&gt;“.  In it he offers a critique of the current linguistic scene as being unclear as to its goals and in need of better definitions. He proposes ‘normal science’ as an alternative:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In many fields of science, comparative research is based on &lt;strong&gt;objective measurements&lt;/strong&gt;, not on categories that are hoped to be universal natural kinds. In linguistics, we can work with objectively defined &lt;strong&gt;comparative concepts&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/1303024&#34;&gt;Haspelmath 2010&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cats and butterflies: 2 misunderstood analogies in scientistic discourse</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/cats-and-butterflies-2-misunderstood-analogies-in-scientistic-discourse/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/cats-and-butterflies-2-misunderstood-analogies-in-scientistic-discourse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Butterfly effect and Schrödinger’s cat are 2 very common ways of signalling one’s belonging to the class of the scientifically literate. But they are almost always told wrong. They were both constructed as illustrations of paradoxes or counterintuitive findings in science. Their retelling always misses the crucial ‘as if’.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an example of metaphor becoming real through its sheer imagistic and rhetorical power. But it also underscores the need to carefully investigate both domains being mapped onto each other, as well as the act of mapping. Metaphors used generatively are only useful if they are abandoned quickly enough. In this case, the popular imagination not only did not abandon the metaphor, it made it into a literal statement with practical consequences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 burning issues in the study of metaphor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/3-burning-issues-in-the-study-of-metaphor/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/3-burning-issues-in-the-study-of-metaphor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how ‘burning’ these issues are as such but if they’re not, I’d propose that they deserve to have some kindling or other accelerant thrown on them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What is the interaction between automatic metaphor processing and deliberate metaphor application?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Metaphors have always been an attractive subjects of study. But they have seen an explosionof interest since ‘Metaphors we live by’ by Lakoff and Johnson. In an almost Freudian turn, these previously seemingly superfluous baubles of language and mind, became central to how we think and speak. All of a sudden, it appeared that metaphors reveal something deeper about our mind that would otherwise remain hidden from view.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 “easy” things that are hard for both humans and AI</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/3-easy-things-that-are-hard-for-both-humans-and-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/3-easy-things-that-are-hard-for-both-humans-and-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Everybody is agog at what AI systems can do. Nobody thought even 10 years ago that machines could be trained to recognise images or transcribe natural speech as well as they do now. And because of this leap forward everybody has started worrying about AI taking over the world because it will soon be able to do everything people can but better.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there are AI naysayers who point at incredible feats of human creativity and ingenuity and say ‘no machines will ever be able to write a poem’ or ‘manage a company’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Innovation is bad for business: 3 more ‘I’ words to compare innovation to</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/innovation-is-bad-for-business-3-more-i-words-to-compare-innovation-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/innovation-is-bad-for-business-3-more-i-words-to-compare-innovation-to/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Innovation is the ‘in’ thing. Innovate or die is the buzz up and down the hive mind. Everybody is feeling like they must innovate all of the things all of the time. But is the incessant innovation the right mode of approaching this?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We constantly spin up stories of the intrepid innovator and the change they bring about in the world. But is that what is really happening on the ground? I think we can bring up some metaphors to bear on this that may open up some different possibilities of conceptualizing innovation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does machine learning produce mental representations?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/does-machine-learning-produce-mental-representations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/does-machine-learning-produce-mental-representations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Why is this important? Many people believe that mental representations are the next goal for ML and a prerequisite for AGI.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Does machine learning produce mental representations equivalent to human ones in kind (if not in quality or quantity)? Definitely not, and there is no clear pathway from current approaches to a place where it would. But it is worth noting that mental representations in humans are also not something straightforward to identify or describe.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Is there a currently viable approach to ML that could eventually lead to mental representations with more engineering? It appears not but then again, no one expected neural nets would get so successful.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Further &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.net/2018/05/does-machine-learning-produce-mental-representations/&#34;&gt;discussion on Reddit&lt;/a&gt;****.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Not ships in the night: Metaphor and simile as process</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/not-ships-in-the-night-metaphor-and-simile-as-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/not-ships-in-the-night-metaphor-and-simile-as-process/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In some circles (rhetoric and analytics philosophy come to mind), much is made of the difference between metaphor and simile.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Rhetoricians pay attention to it because they like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Figure_of_speech&#34;&gt;taxonomies&lt;/a&gt; of communicative devices and analytic philosophers spend time on it because of their commitment to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truth-conditional_semantics&#34;&gt;a truth-theoretical account of meaning&lt;/a&gt; and naive assumptions about compositionality).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is true that their surface and communicative differences have an impact in certain contexts but if we’re interested in the conceptual underpinnings of metaphor, we’re more likely to ignore the distinction altogether.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to read ‘Women, Fire and Dangerous Things’: Guide to essential reading on human cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/how-to-read-women-fire-and-dangerous-things-guide-to-essential-reading-on-human-cognition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/how-to-read-women-fire-and-dangerous-things-guide-to-essential-reading-on-human-cognition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;note&#34;&gt;Note:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These are rough notes for a metaphor reading group, not a continuous narrative. Any comments, corrections or elaborations are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-should-you-read-wfdt&#34;&gt;Why should you read WFDT?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Women, Fire, and Dangerous Things: What Categories Reveal About the Mind&lt;/strong&gt; is still a significantly underappreciated and (despite its high citation count) not-enough-read book that has a lot to contribute to thinking about how the mind works.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think it provides one of the most concise and explicit models for how to think about the mind and language from a cognitive perspective. I also find its argument against the still prevalent approach to language and the mind as essentially fixed objects very compelling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Therapy for Frege: A brief outline of the theory of everything</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/therapy-for-frege-a-brief-outline-of-the-theory-of-everything/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/therapy-for-frege-a-brief-outline-of-the-theory-of-everything/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;freges-trauma&#34;&gt;Frege’s trauma&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I found the following quote from Frege on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://languagegoesonholiday.blogspot.co.uk/2018/05/fixing-frege.html&#34;&gt;Language goes on holiday blog&lt;/a&gt; and it struck as the perfect starting point for this essay which has been written for a while now:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Frege (“Logic in Mathematics”): Definitions proper must be distinguished from elucidations [Erläuterungen]. In the first stages of any discipline we cannot avoid the use of ordinary words. But these words are, for the most part, not really appropriate for scientific purposes, because they are not precise enough and fluctuate in their use. Science needs technical terms that have precise and fixed Bedeutungen, and in order to come to an understanding about these Bedeutungen and exclude possible misunderstandings, we provide elucidations. Of course in so doing we have again to use ordinary words, and these may display defects similar to those which the elucidations are intended to remove. So it seems that we shall then have to provide further elucidations. Theoretically one will never really achieve one’s goal in this way. In practice, however, we do manage to come to an understanding about the Bedeutungen of words. Of course we have to be able to count on a meeting of minds, on others’ guessing what we have in mind.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 ways in which music is like language and 8 (more important) ways in which it is not</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/10-ways-in-which-music-is-like-language-and-8-more-important-ways-in-which-it-is-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/10-ways-in-which-music-is-like-language-and-8-more-important-ways-in-which-it-is-not/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People often talk about music as if it were language. Leonard Bernstein even recorded a series of lectures applying &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MB7ZOdp__gQ&#34;&gt;Chomsky’s theory of generative grammar to music&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kojvij-PNq8&#34;&gt;Chomsky himself&lt;/a&gt; answered a question on this in a not very satisfying manner. Some people can get very exercised over this.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But it seems to me that a playing around with strengths and weakness of the music = language metaphor can help us come to grips with the question a bit better. We can find a number of mappings between music and language but an equal number of mis-mappings. We do not need to go very far into it to see where they are. That does not mean that a deeper investigation into musical properties of language and linguistic properties of music cannot be fruitful. And obviously they are both universal human faculties — but looking for a musical essence in language or a linguistic essence in music is what a metaphor-aware approach to this question is hoping to warn against.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 ways in which music is like language and 8 (more important) ways in which it is not</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/10-ways-in-which-music-is-like-language-and-8-more-important-ways-in-which-it-is/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/10-ways-in-which-music-is-like-language-and-8-more-important-ways-in-which-it-is/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People often talk about music as if it were language. Leonard Bernstein even recorded a series of lectures applying &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MB7ZOdp__gQ&#34;&gt;Chomsky’s theory of generative grammar to music&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kojvij-PNq8&#34;&gt;Chomsky himself&lt;/a&gt; answered a question on this in a not very satisfying manner. Some people can get very exercised over this.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But it seems to me that a playing around with strengths and weakness of the music = language metaphor can help us come to grips with the question a bit better. We can find a number of mappings between music and language but an equal number of mis-mappings. We do not need to go very far into it to see where they are. That does not mean that a deeper investigation into musical properties of language and linguistic properties of music cannot be fruitful. And obviously they are both universal human faculties — but looking for a musical essence in language or a linguistic essence in music is what a metaphor aware approach to this question is hoping to warn against.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 Things Everyone Should Know About Language But Doesn’t Even Know to Ask</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/17-things-everyone-should-know-about-language-but-doesnt-even-know-to-ask/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/17-things-everyone-should-know-about-language-but-doesnt-even-know-to-ask/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Languages are not a simple matter of grammar. Any language policy must consider what is known about language from the fields of pragmatics, sociolinguistics, and cognitive linguistics. Here I collected, 17 key findings about language from across many fields of linguistic inquiry. These are descriptive things we know with some certainty about how language works.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Who should know these things? Everyone would be a nice thing but in the absence of that, I’d settle for some of these: Teachers and especially language teachers. Journalists. Language policy experts. And (and here we’re just praying for a miracle) grammar mavens.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fruit loops and metaphors: Metaphors are not about explaining the abstract through concrete but…</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-throug/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-throug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-through-concrete-but-about-the-dynamic-process-of-negotiated-sensemaking&#34;&gt;Fruit loops and metaphors: Metaphors are not about explaining the abstract through concrete but about the dynamic process of negotiated sensemaking&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/960/1*_T0MTlgi3p0CjzWNmCYDIg.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the less fortunate consequences of the popularity of the conceptual metaphor paradigm (which is also the one I by and large work with) is the highlighting of the embodied metaphor at the expenses of others. This gives the impression that metaphors are there to explain more abstract concepts in terms of more concrete ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning vs training in machines and organizations: Production of knowledge vs production of…</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/learning-vs-training-in-machines-and-organizations-production-of-knowledge-vs-pr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/learning-vs-training-in-machines-and-organizations-production-of-knowledge-vs-pr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-vs-training-in-machines-and-organizations-production-of-knowledge-vs-production-of-capabilityexploration-of-metaphors&#34;&gt;Learning vs training in machines and organizations: Production of knowledge vs production of capability — Exploration of metaphors&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*EAv0CPYrJ99vgSIkp-jnJg.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;machine-learning-is-to-organizational-learningas&#34;&gt;Machine learning is to organizational learning as…&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sbs.ox.ac.uk/school/events-0/david-upton-memorial-lecture&#34;&gt;recent lecture by Gary Pisano&lt;/a&gt; made the parallel between machine learning and organizational learning in the sense that they are both processes that produce knowledge. My immediate reaction was that they are not alike because machine learning is really a misnomer. Or rather machine learning has some aspects of learning but is dissimilar from prototypical learning in enough ways to make the analogy dangerous. But my second thought was that actually organizational learning and prototypical learning are dissimilar in the same ways that machine learning and prototypical learning are. We could then learn more about both if we look at the various mappings and mismappings (a sort of metaphor hack).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quick notes on measurement: Measuring anything and nothing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2017/quick-notes-on-measurement-measuring-anything-and-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2017/quick-notes-on-measurement-measuring-anything-and-nothing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*7DXn-l5lH1F1zmxAUsF-Jg.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;note&#34;&gt;Note:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These were supposed to be quick notes. But they ain’t. Be warned.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://rationallyspeakingpodcast.org/show/rs-197-doug-hubbard-on-why-people-think-some-things-cant-be.html&#34;&gt;Rationally Speaking&lt;/a&gt; podcast Julia Galef and Doug Hubbard discussed the notion of ‘How to Measure Anything’. This is not a screed against daring to assign numerical values. I think we need to start from the premise that everything that Juia and Doug said is correct. However, I want to show that even with that premise, the intuitive objections to assigning numerical values to human values are still necessary. And in fact, if we object on these grounds, we can see that in fact we can measure nothing while we can still benefit from using tools of measurement to think about complex problems. But these tools are metaphors about those problems — they are not describing some hidden true essence — they are giving us a way of thinking about them. And as with any metaphors, we need to reject them as often as take them for our own.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guns, Glory, and Greed: Most wars were not caused by religion (but they weren’t prevented by it…</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2017/guns-glory-and-greed-most-wars-were-not-caused-by-religion-but-they-werent-preve/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2017/guns-glory-and-greed-most-wars-were-not-caused-by-religion-but-they-werent-preve/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;guns-glory-and-greed-most-wars-were-not-caused-by-religion-but-they-werent-prevented-by-iteither&#34;&gt;Guns, Glory, and Greed: Most wars were not caused by religion (but they weren’t prevented by it either)&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lots of people say things like ‘religion causes war’&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But looking at a list of wars shows that relatively few are ‘caused’ by religion&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Religion does not stop wars and is often used to bolster the case — but it is rarely the primary causal agent&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What causes wars is: 1) &lt;strong&gt;Guns:&lt;/strong&gt; Availability of means to wage war (not literally guns) 2) &lt;strong&gt;Glory:&lt;/strong&gt; A framework within which the war makes sense (makes people feel good about fighting it) 3) &lt;strong&gt;Greed:&lt;/strong&gt; A desire for resources&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But all of this is even more complicated because neither &lt;em&gt;war&lt;/em&gt; not &lt;em&gt;religion&lt;/em&gt; are straightforward concepts that can be easily entered into some sort of causality identification algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;historical-note&#34;&gt;Historical Note&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I wrote this about 2 years ago but I felt it needed more thought. Now, that I’ve reread it with some distance, I find that I have very little to add. I have found a few new things (for instance about the religious discourse around many of the Persian wars) but nothing that would make me alter the basic outline. So, here it goes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repaved paths and generative metaphors: Expressing human purposes with technology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2016/repaved-paths-and-generative-metaphors-expressing-human-purposes-with-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2016/repaved-paths-and-generative-metaphors-expressing-human-purposes-with-technology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This is an edited version of my side of a discussion on an education technology mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I fully subscribe to the idea of thinking about pedagogy as being a type of technology (so are cultural institutions according to anthropologists and many people even think of language that way). But most people think of technology as ‘digital technology’ which is how ‘education technology’ is used. For them technology is a real or virtual machine that performs tasks independent of human intervention or in response to basic human actions. What I find most useful is switching between the two perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>History as weather: A fractal theory of history for Ian Morris, Jared Diamond and CGP Grey</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2016/history-as-weather-a-fractal-theory-of-history-for-ian-morris-jared-diamond-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2016/history-as-weather-a-fractal-theory-of-history-for-ian-morris-jared-diamond-and/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*5o_VsnRC1R-ZYXKYiAbnFw.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;outline-of-theargument&#34;&gt;Outline of the argument&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;History of often accused of not being sufficiently scientific. To remedy this people try to come up with all sorts of theories of history that try to look like science. They come up with some measurable variable (e.g. availability of domesticable species as Jared Diamond did or energy output as Ian Morris did or size of population, advancement of technology, size of armies, etc. as many others do). This, they hope, explains the past and predicts the future. Based on the theories, the would-be-scientist-historians build models that seem to make perfect sense but seemingly fall apart when overtaken by events. This makes history seem like it’s not at all scientific. But that’s only because we’re comparing it to the very rare instances in science where long-term perfect prediction is possible. Like the motions of planetary bodies or the behavior of a computer. But in most cases, science struggles with perfect prediction. In medicine, it’s impossible to predict the exact course a disease will take in any one individual, even though it is often possible to predict what course it will take over a thousand individuals. In biology, it is impossible to predict, which features will be selected over others through natural selection. But it is possible to predict that some will be. But the best analogy, to my mind, is the weather.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What language looks like: Dictionary and grammar are to language what standing on one foot is to running</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-language-looks-like-dictionary-and-grammar-are-to-language-what-standing-on-one-foot-is-to-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-language-looks-like-dictionary-and-grammar-are-to-language-what-standing-on-one-foot-is-to-running/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a rather obscure and complex analogy just clicks into place in one’s mind and allows a slightly altered way of thinking that just makes so much sense it hurts. Like putting glasses on in the morning and the world suddenly snapping into shape.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This happened to me this morning when reading the &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychsciencenotes.blogspot.co.uk/2014/10/do-people-really-not-know-what-running.html&#34;&gt;Notes from Two Scientific Psychologists blog&lt;/a&gt; and the post &lt;em&gt;Do people really not know what running looks like?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anthropologists’ metaphorical shenanigans: Or how (not) to research metaphor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/anthropologists-metaphorical-shenanigans-or-how-not-to-research-metaphor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/anthropologists-metaphorical-shenanigans-or-how-not-to-research-metaphor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over on the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://genealogyreligion.net/invisible-disenchantments&#34;&gt;‘Genealogy of Religion’&lt;/a&gt;, Cris Campbell waved a friendly red rag in front of my eyes to make me incensed over exaggerated claims (some) anthropologists make about metaphors. I had expressed some doubts in previous comments but felt that perhaps this particular one deserves its own post.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The book Cris refers to is a collection of essays  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/America-1492-Peoples-Arrival-Columbus/dp/0679743375&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;America in 1492: The World of the Indian Peoples Before the Arrival of Columbus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(1991, ed. Alvin Josephy) which also contains an essay by Joel Sherzer called “A Richness of Voices”.  I don’t have the book but I looked up a few quotes on metaphor from the book.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does it mean when words ‘really’ mean something: Dismiss the Miss</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-does-it-mean-when-words-really-mean-something-dismiss-the-miss/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-does-it-mean-when-words-really-mean-something-dismiss-the-miss/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I tweeted a link to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tes.co.uk/article.aspx?storycode=6427726&#34;&gt;article in TES&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today, I got the following response back:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;@lizzielh is absolutely right. As the title of an as yet unpublished blog post of mine goes: &lt;strong&gt;“Words don’t mean things, people mean things”&lt;/strong&gt;. I even wrote a whole &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/7069654/What_does_it_mean_when_texts_really_mean_something_Types_of_evidence_for_conceptual_patterns_in_discourse&#34;&gt;book chapter on that with the same title as this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, if it had been me writing on the topic, I would have chosen a more judicious title. Such as “The legacy of discrimination behind the humble Miss” or “Past and present inequalities encoded in the simple Miss”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is not a metaphor: Modelling the world through language, thought, science, or action</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-is-not-a-metaphor-modelling-the-world-through-language-thought-science-or-action/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/what-is-not-a-metaphor-modelling-the-world-through-language-thought-science-or-action/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-role-of-metaphor-in-science-debate-background&#34;&gt;The role of metaphor in science debate (Background)&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Recently, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lse.ac.uk/newsAndMedia/videoAndAudio/channels/publicLecturesAndEvents/player.aspx?id=2289&#34;&gt;LSE podcast an interesting panel on the subject of “Metaphors and Science”&lt;/a&gt;. It featured three speakers talking about the interface between metaphor and various ‘scientific’ disciplines (economics, physics and surgery). Unlike many such occasions, all speakers were actually very knowledgeable and thoughtful on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In particular, I liked Felicity Mellor and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lse.ac.uk/researchAndexpertise/experts/profile.aspx?KeyValue=r.bronk%40lse.ac.uk&#34;&gt;Richard Bronk&lt;/a&gt; who adopted the same perspective that underlies this blog and which I most recently articulated in &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.net/2013/10/pervasiveness-of-oblidging-metaphors-in-thought-and-deed&#34;&gt;writing about obliging metaphors&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imperial.ac.uk/AP/faces/pages/read/Home.jsp?person=f.mellor&amp;amp;_adf.ctrl-state=g30lcwtcs_3&amp;amp;_afrRedirect=1604205418236000&#34;&gt;Felicity Mellor&lt;/a&gt; put it especially eloquently when she said:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linguistics according to Fillmore</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/linguistics-according-to-fillmore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/linguistics-according-to-fillmore/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While people keep banging on about &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2010/08/why-chomsky-doesnt-count-as-a-gifted-linguist/&#34; title=&#34;Why Chomsky doesn’t count as a gifted linguist&#34;&gt;Chomsky&lt;/a&gt; as being the be all and end all of linguistics (I’m looking at you philosophers of language), there have been many linguists who have had a much more substantial impact on how we actually think about language in a way that matters. In my post on why &lt;a href=&#34;http://metaphorhacker.techczech.net/2010/08/why-chomsky-doesnt-count-as-a-gifted-linguist/&#34; title=&#34;Why Chomsky doesn’t count as a gifted linguist&#34;&gt;Chomsky is not really a linguist at all&lt;/a&gt; I listed a few.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 things everybody should know about language: Outline of linguistics’ contribution to the liberal arts curriculum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/5-things-everybody-should-know-about-language-outline-of-linguistics-contribution-to-the-liberal-arts-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2014/5-things-everybody-should-know-about-language-outline-of-linguistics-contribution-to-the-liberal-arts-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;drafty&#34;&gt;Drafty&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This was written in some haste and needs further refinement. Maybe one day that will come. For now, it will be left as it stands.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This post outlines what I think are the key learnings from the output of the research of the field of linguistics that should be reflected in the general curriculum (in as much as any should be). This is in reaction to the recent posts by Mark Liberman suggesting the role and form of grammar analysis in general education. I argue that he is almost entirely wrong in his assumptions as well as in his emphasis. I will outline my arguments against his position at the end of the post. At the beginning I will outline key easily digestible lessons of modern linguistics that should be incorporated into language education at all levels.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binders full of women with mighty pens: What is metonymy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/binders-full-of-women-with-mighty-pens-what-is-metonymy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/binders-full-of-women-with-mighty-pens-what-is-metonymy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Metonymy in the wild&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://25.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_md37c5dYtG1rj8amio1_1280.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://25.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_md37c5dYtG1rj8amio1_1280.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Things were not going well for Mitt Romney in early autumn of last year. And then he responded to a query about gender equality with this sentence:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I had the chance to pull together a cabinet, and all the applicants seemed to be men… I went to a number of women’s groups and said, ‘Can you help us find folks?’ and they brought us whole binders full of women.” &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binders&#34;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binders&lt;/a&gt;_full_of_women&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three books of the year 2013 and some books of the century 1900-2013</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/three-books-of-the-year-2013-and-some-books-of-the-century-1900-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/three-books-of-the-year-2013-and-some-books-of-the-century-1900-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been asked (as every year) to nominate three books of the year for Lidové Noviny (a Czech paper I contribute to occasionally). This is always a tough choice for me and some years I don’t even bother responding. This is because I don’t tend to read books ‘of the moment’ and range widely in my reading across time periods. But I think I have some good ones this time. Additionally, Lidové Noviny are celebrating 120 years of being a major Czech newspaper so they also asked me for a book of the century (since 1900 till now). It makes no sense to even try to pick ‘the one’, so I picked three categories that are of interest to me (language, society and fiction) and chose three books in each.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pervasiveness of Obliging Metaphors in Thought and Deed</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/pervasiveness-of-obliging-metaphors-in-thought-and-deed/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/pervasiveness-of-obliging-metaphors-in-thought-and-deed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“when history is at its most obliging, the history-writer needs be at his most wary.” (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/China-History-John-Keay/dp/0007221789&#34;&gt;China by John Keay&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/16230215@N08/6220425549/&#34; title=&#34;Die Mykologen - Glückspilze - Lucky Fellows - Fungi Experts&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6166/6220425549_cc19140a63.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Die Mykologen - Glückspilze - Lucky Fellows - Fungi Experts&#34; title=&#34;Die Mykologen - Glückspilze - Lucky Fellows - Fungi Experts&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I came across this nugget of wisdom when I was re-reading the Introduction to John Keay’s history of China. And it struck me that in some way this quote could be a part of the motto of this blog. The whole thing might then read something like this:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Storms in all Teacups: The Power and Inequality in the Battle for Science Universality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/storms-in-all-teacups-the-power-and-inequality-in-the-battle-for-science-universality/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/storms-in-all-teacups-the-power-and-inequality-in-the-battle-for-science-universality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The great blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://genealogyreligion.net/salubrious-storm&#34;&gt;Genealogy of Religion&lt;/a&gt; posted this video with a somewhat approving commentary:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The video started off with panache and promised some entertainment, however, I found myself increasingly annoyed as the video continued. The problem is that this is an exchange of cliches that pretends to be a fight of truth against ignorance. Sure, Storm doesn’t put forward a very coherent argument for her position, but neither does Minchin. His description of science vs. faith is laughable (being in awe at the size of the universe, my foot) and nowhere does he display any nuance nor, frankly, any evidence that he is doing anything other than parroting what he’s heard on some TV interview with Dawkins. I have much more sympathy with the Storms of this world than these self-styled defenders of science whose only credentials are that they can remember a bit of high school physics or chemistry and have read an article by some neo-atheist in Wired. What’s worse, it’s would be rationalists like him who do what passes for science reporting in major newspapers or on the BBC.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How we use metaphors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/how-we-use-metaphors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/how-we-use-metaphors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was reminded by &lt;a href=&#34;http://thelousylinguist.blogspot.co.uk/2013/04/the-birth-of-metaphor.html&#34;&gt;this blog post on LousyLinguist&lt;/a&gt; that many people still see metaphor as an unproblematic homogeneous concept leading to much circular thinking about them.  I wrote about that quite a few years ago in:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lukeš, D., 2005. Towards a classification of metaphor use in text: Issues in conceptual discourse analysis of a domain-specific corpus. In &lt;em&gt;Third Workshop on Corpus-Based Approaches to Figurative Language&lt;/em&gt;. Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I suggested that a classification of metaphor had better focused on their use rather than inherent nature. I came up with the heuristic device of: cognitive, social and textual uses of metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do we need a gaming literacy: Literacy metaphor hack</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/do-we-need-a-gaming-literacy-literacy-metaphor-hack/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/do-we-need-a-gaming-literacy-literacy-metaphor-hack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-am-a-gaming-semi-literate&#34;&gt;I am a gaming semi-literate!&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was listening to the discussion of the latest BioShock game on &lt;a href=&#34;http://twit.tv/show/this-week-in-tech/399&#34;&gt;the latest TWiT podcast&lt;/a&gt; when I realized that I am in fact game illiterate. I am hearing these stories and descriptions of experiences but I know I can’t access them directly without a major investment in knowledge and skill acquisition. So, this is what people with no or limited literacy must feel like in highly literacy-dependent environments. I really want to access the stories in the way they are told by the game. But I know I can’t. I will stumble, be discouraged, not have a very good time before I can have a good time. I will be a struggling gamer, in the same way that there are struggling readers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Framing and constructions as a bridge between cognition and culture: Two Abstracts for Cognitive Futures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/framing-and-constructions-as-a-bridge-between-cognition-and-culture-two-abstracts-for-cognitive-futures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/framing-and-constructions-as-a-bridge-between-cognition-and-culture-two-abstracts-for-cognitive-futures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just found out that both abstracts I submitted to the Cognitive Futures of the Humanities Conference were accepted. I was really only expecting one to get through but I’m looking forward to talking about the ideas in both.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first first talk has foundations in a paper I wrote almost 5 years ago now about the nature of evidence for discourse. But the idea is pretty much central to all my thinking on the subject of culture and cognition. The challenge as I see it is to come up with a cognitively realistic but not a cognitively reductionist account of culture. And the problem I see is that often the learning only goes one way. The people studying culture are supposed to be learning about the results of research on cognition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The complexities of simple: What simple language proponents should know about linguistics [updated]</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2012/the-complexities-of-simple-what-simple-language-proponents-should-know-about-linguistics-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2012/the-complexities-of-simple-what-simple-language-proponents-should-know-about-linguistics-updated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;update&#34;&gt;Update&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Part of this post was incorporated into an article I wrote with Brian Kelly and Alistair McNaught that appeared in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue70/kelly-et-al&#34;&gt;the December issue of Ariadne&lt;/a&gt;. As part of that work and feedback from Alistair and Brian, I expanded the final section from a simple list of bullets into a more detailed research programme. You can see it below and in the article.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-from-spelling-reform-to-plain-language&#34;&gt;Background: From spelling reform to plain language&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/12836528@N00/4843655940&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4149/4843655940_a8479f5c4d_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Simple&#34; title=&#34;Simple&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cliches, information and metaphors: Overcoming prejudice with metahor hacking and getting it back again</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2012/cliches-information-and-metaphors-overcoming-prejudice-with-metahor-hacking-and-getting-it-back-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2012/cliches-information-and-metaphors-overcoming-prejudice-with-metahor-hacking-and-getting-it-back-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/95674706@N00/2312975911&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3198/2312975911_c4323e9436_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Professor Abhijit Banerjee&#34; title=&#34;Professor Abhijit Banerjee&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Professor Abhijit Banerjee (Photo credit: kalyan3)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“We have to use &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clich%C3%A9&#34; title=&#34;Cliché&#34;&gt;cliches&lt;/a&gt;,” said professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abhijit_Banerjee&#34; title=&#34;Abhijit Banerjee&#34;&gt;Abhijit Banerjee&lt;/a&gt; at the start of his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.lse.ac.uk/publicEvents/events/2012/03/20120326t1830vSZT.aspx&#34;&gt;LSE lecture on Poor Economics&lt;/a&gt;. “The world is just too complicated.” He continued. “Which is why it is all the more important, we choose the right cliches.” [I’m paraphrasing here.]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an insight at the very heart of linguistics. Every language act we are a part of is an act of categorization. There are no simple unitary terms in language. When I say, “pull up a chair”, I’m in fact referring to a vast category of objects we refer to as chairs. These objects are not identified by any one set of features like four legs, certain height, certain ways of using it. There is no minimal set of features that will describe all chairs and just chairs and not other kinds of objects like tables or pillows. But chairs don’t stand on their own. They are related to other concepts or categories (and they are really one and the same). There are subcategories like stools and armchairs, containing categories like furniture or man-made objects and related categories like houses and shops selling objects. All of these categories are linked in our minds through a complex set of images, stories and definitions. But these don’t just live in our minds. They also appear in our conversations. So we say things like, “What kind of a chair would you like to buy?”, “That’s not real chair”, “What’s the point of a chair if you can’t sit in it?”, “Stools are not chairs.”, “It’s more of a couch than a chair.”, “Sofas are really just big plush chairs, when it comes down to it.”, “I’m using a box for a chair.”, “Don’t sit on a table, it’s not a chair.” Etc. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category_of_being&#34; title=&#34;Category of being&#34;&gt;Categories&lt;/a&gt; are not stable and uniform across all people, so we continue having conversations about them. There are experts on chairs, historians of chairs, chair craftsmen, people who buy chairs for a living, people who study the word ‘chair’, and people who casually use chairs. Some more than others. And their sets of stories and images and definitions related to chairs will be slightly different. And they will have had different types of conversations with different people about chairs. All of that goes into a simple word like “chair”. It’s really very simple as long as we accept the complexity for what it is. Philosophers of language have made a right mess of things because they tried to find simplicity where none exists. And what’s more where none is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-education as a weapon: Beyond the ridiculous in linguistic prescriptivism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2012/pseudo-education-as-a-weapon-beyond-the-ridiculous-in-linguistic-prescriptivism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2012/pseudo-education-as-a-weapon-beyond-the-ridiculous-in-linguistic-prescriptivism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Teacher_in_Laos.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/40/Teacher_in_Laos.jpg/300px-Teacher_in_Laos.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Teacher in primary school in northern Laos&#34; title=&#34;Teacher in primary school in northern Laos&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Teacher in primary school in northern Laos (Photo credit: Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most of us are all too happy to repeat clichés about education to motivate ourselves and others to engage in this liminal ritual of mass socialization. One such phrase is “knowledge is power”. It is used to refer not just to education, of course, but to all sorts of intelligence gathering from business to politics. We tell many stories of how knowing something made the difference, from knowing a way of making something to work to knowing a secret only the hero or villain is privy to. But in education, in particular, it is not just knowing that matters to our tribe but also the display of knowing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Character Assasination through Metaphoric Pomposity: When one metaphor is not enough</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2012/character-assasination-through-metaphoric-pomposity-when-one-metaphor-is-not-enough/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2012/character-assasination-through-metaphoric-pomposity-when-one-metaphor-is-not-enough/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;George Lakoff is known for saying that “metaphors can kill” and he’s not wrong. But in that, metaphors are no different from any other language. The simple amoral imperative “Kill!” will do the job just as nicely. Nor are metaphors any better or worse at obfuscating than any other type of language. But they are very good at their primary purpose which is making complex connections between domains.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Metaphors can create very powerful connections where none existed before. And we are just as often seduced by that power as inspired to new heights of creativity. We don’t really have a choice. Metaphoric thinking is in our DNA (itself a metaphor). But just like with DNA, context is important, and sometimes metaphors work for us and sometimes they work against us. The more powerful they are, the more cautious we need to be. When faced with powerful metaphors we should always look for alternatives and we should also explore the limits of the metaphors and the connections they make. We need to keep in mind that nothing IS anything else but everything is LIKE something else.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moral Compass Metaphor Points to Surprising Places</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/moral-compass-metaphor-points-to-surprising-places/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/moral-compass-metaphor-points-to-surprising-places/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I thought the moral compass metaphor has mostly left current political discourse but it just cropped up – this time pointing from left to right – as [David Plouffe accused Mitt Romney of not having one]((&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/political-animal/2011_10/no_core033193.php)&#34;&gt;http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/political-animal/2011_10/no_core033193.php)&lt;/a&gt;. As I keep repeating, George Lakoff once said “Metaphors can kill.” And Moral Compass has certainly done its share of homicidal damage. Justifying wars, interventions and unflinching black and white resolve in the face of gray circumstances. It is a killer metaphor!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Killer App is a bad metaphor for historical trends, good for pseudoteaching</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/killer-app-is-a-bad-metaphor-for-historical-trends-good-for-pseudoteaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/killer-app-is-a-bad-metaphor-for-historical-trends-good-for-pseudoteaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Latin_alphabet_world_distribution.svg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/f/f4/Latin_alphabet_world_distribution.svg/300px-Latin_alphabet_world_distribution.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;This map shows the countries in the world that&amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;This map shows the countries in the world that...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niall_Ferguson&#34; title=&#34;Niall Ferguson&#34;&gt;Niall Ferguson&lt;/a&gt; wrote in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/education/2011/mar/29/history-school-crisis-disconnected-events&#34;&gt;The Guardian some time ago&lt;/a&gt; about how awful history education has become with these “new-fangled” 40-year-old methods like focusing on “history skills” that leads to kids leaving school knowing “unconnected fragments of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_world&#34; title=&#34;Western world&#34;&gt;Western history&lt;/a&gt;: Henry VIII and Hitler, with a small dose of Martin Luther King, Jr.” but not who was the reigning English monarch at the time of the Armada. Instead, he wants history to be taught his way: deep trends leading to the understanding why the “West” rules and why Fergusson is the cleverest of all the historians that ever lived. He even provided (and how cute is this) a lesson plan!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Language learning in literature as a source domain for generative metaphors about anything</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/language-learning-in-literature-as-a-source-domain-for-generative-metaphors-about-anything/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/language-learning-in-literature-as-a-source-domain-for-generative-metaphors-about-anything/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Minamoto_no_Yoritomo.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/76/Minamoto_no_Yoritomo.jpg/300px-Minamoto_no_Yoritomo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Portrait of Yoritomo, copy of the 1179 origina&amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;Portrait of Yoritomo, copy of the 1179 origina...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my thinking about things human, I often like to draw on the domain of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_language_acquisition&#34; title=&#34;Second language acquisition&#34;&gt;second language learning&lt;/a&gt; as the source of analogies. The problem is that relatively few people in the English speaking world have experience with language learning to such an extent that they can actually map things onto it. In fact, in my experience, even people who have a lot of experience with language learning are actually not aware of all the things that were happening while they were learning. And of course awareness of research or language learning theories is not to be expected. This is not helped by the language teaching profession’s propaganda that language learning is “fun” and “rewarding” (whatever that is). In fact my mantra of language learning (I learned from my friend Bill Perry) is that “language learning is hard and takes time” – at least if you expect to achieve a level of competence above that of “impressing the natives” with your “please” and “thank you”. In that, language learning is like any other human endeavor but because of its relatively bounded nature — when compared to, for instance, culture — it can be particularly illuminating.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The natural logistics of life: The Internet really changes almost nothing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-natural-logistics-of-life-the-internet-really-changes-almost-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-natural-logistics-of-life-the-internet-really-changes-almost-nothing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Youve-Got-Mail-Tom-Hanks/dp/6305368171%3FSubscriptionId%3D0G81C5DAZ03ZR9WH9X82%26tag%3Dzemanta-20%26linkCode%3Dxm2%26camp%3D2025%26creative%3D165953%26creativeASIN%3D6305368171&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51JN65AE3YL._SL300_.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cover of &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;ve Got Mail&amp;rdquo;&#34; title=&#34;Cover of &amp;quot;You&#39;ve Got Mail&amp;quot;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cover of You&amp;rsquo;ve Got Mail&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a post that has been germinating for a long time. But it was most immediately inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshall_Poe&#34; title=&#34;Marshall Poe&#34;&gt;Marshall Poe&lt;/a&gt;‘s article claiming that “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hnn.us/articles/133910.html&#34;&gt;The Internet Changes Nothing&lt;/a&gt;“. And as it turns out, I mostly agree.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OK, this may sound a bit paradoxical. Twelve years ago, when I submitted my first column to be published, I delivered the text to my editor on a diskette. Now, I don’t even have an editor (or at least not for this kind of writing). I just click a button and my text is published. But! If my server logs are to be trusted, it will be read by 10s or at best 100s of people over its lifetime. That’s more than if I’d just written some notes to myself or published it in an academic journal but much less than if I publish it in a national daily with a readership of hundreds of thousands. Not all of them will read what I write but more than would on this blog.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;So while democratising the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Publishing&#34; title=&#34;Publishing&#34;&gt;publishing industry&lt;/a&gt; has worked for Kos, Huffington and many others, still many more blogs languish in obscurity. I can say anything I want but my voice matters little in the cacophony.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When is subtle manipulation of data a flat out lie? Truth about Chinese prisons [UPDATE]</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/when-is-subtle-manipulation-of-data-a-flat-out-lie-truth-about-chinese-prisons-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/when-is-subtle-manipulation-of-data-a-flat-out-lie-truth-about-chinese-prisons-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/China&#34; title=&#34;China&#34;&gt;China&lt;/a&gt; kick lately (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/China-History-John-Keay/dp/0007221789/&#34;&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chinahistorypodcast.com&#34;&gt;listening&lt;/a&gt; about its history and global position) and a crime public policy kick (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/When-Brute-Force-Fails-Punishment/dp/0691148643&#34;&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcast.oid.ucla.edu/courses/2009-2010/2010winter/pp10a-1/podcast.xml&#34;&gt;listening&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_A.R._Kleiman&#34; title=&#34;Mark A.R. Kleiman&#34;&gt;Mark Kleiman&lt;/a&gt;). I was struck when I heard Mark say in an interview that the US has more people in jail in absolute terms than China. So I went about to looking for some data. I found the most comprehensive source of info in the “&lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;amp;q=cache:lzGQNLGCeZ0J:www.kcl.ac.uk/depsta/law/research/icps/downloads/world-prison-pop-seventh.pdf+chinese+prison+population&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;gl=uk&amp;amp;pid=bl&amp;amp;srcid=ADGEESi8tLqSmM3bovvLsczZmFxd77uSek8aIbQTiiWsO14Y9ea0iMrb1RVVoclUbZ9wWTZq4i4f5XQwew_ehsS63rnVYyAG8yodlBOluLcRY3heNMf1jYkvOKpD--2NOypl1P30vuUC&amp;amp;sig=AHIEtbScQOPaOogNCd2X81PAVQhcUMRI9Q&#34;&gt;World Prison Population List&lt;/a&gt;” published by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://maps.google.com/maps?ll=51.5119444444,-0.116111111111&amp;amp;spn=0.01,0.01&amp;amp;q=51.5119444444,-0.116111111111%20(King%27s%20College%20London)&amp;amp;t=h&#34; title=&#34;King&#39;s College London&#34;&gt;King’s College London&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Centre_for_Prison_Studies&#34; title=&#34;International Centre for Prison Studies&#34;&gt;International Centre for Prison Studies&lt;/a&gt;. Their top bullet point is alarming:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I object: A male feminist’s view on the Duchess of Cambridge’s Wedding dress</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/i-object-a-male-feminists-view-on-the-duchess-of-cambridges-wedding-dress/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/i-object-a-male-feminists-view-on-the-duchess-of-cambridges-wedding-dress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/16061323@N07/5664356426&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5144/5664356426_e656ccff2a_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Welcome to our wedding&#34; title=&#34;Welcome to our wedding&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image by bobfranklin (mostly tacit) via Flickr&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Maybe I should be watching more TV but I honestly had no idea what &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kate_Middleton&#34; title=&#34;Kate Middleton&#34;&gt;Kate Middleton&lt;/a&gt; looked like. There must have been times I would have heard references to her and thought she was some kind of actress or model. And frankly, I still don’t care.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But I do care about her dress. I am quite naive in the way of things (despite my interest in the ethnography of the everyday) so the fact that it may matter what the future queen will be wearing on her wedding day was not obvious to me. And matter more to many than whether a former prime minister or two were invited. I heard about it on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/today/&#34; title=&#34;Today (BBC Radio 4)&#34;&gt;Today programme&lt;/a&gt; this morning and realised that I had been pretty silly not to have thought about it and then all was clear when I got a text from a female friend who professed that the dress was the main thing of import.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poetry without metaphor? Sure but can it darn your socks?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/poetry-without-metaphor-sure-but-can-it-darn-your-socks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/poetry-without-metaphor-sure-but-can-it-darn-your-socks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:LiBai.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4c/LiBai.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Chinese poet Li Bai from the Tang dynasty, in &amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;Chinese poet Li Bai from the Tang dynasty, in ...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://languagelog.ldc.upenn.edu/nll/?p=3108&#34; title=&#34;Language Log&#34;&gt;Language Log&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_H._Mair&#34; title=&#34;Victor H. Mair&#34;&gt;Victor Mair&lt;/a&gt; puts to rest that all English expressions have to be tensed and thus prevent timeless poetry. He shares his translation of a 13th century &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Chinese_language_poets&#34; title=&#34;List of Chinese language poets&#34;&gt;Chinese poet&lt;/a&gt; thus:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Autumn Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ma_Zhiyuan&#34;&gt;Ma Zhiyuan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Withered wisteria, old tree, darkling crows –&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Little bridge over flowing water by someone’s house –&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Emaciated horse on an ancient road in the western wind –&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Evening sun setting in the west –&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Broken-hearted man on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Religion, if it exists, is negotiation of underdetermined metaphoric cognition [UPDATED]</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/religion-if-it-exists-is-negotiation-of-underdetermined-metaphoric-cognition-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/religion-if-it-exists-is-negotiation-of-underdetermined-metaphoric-cognition-updated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;preamble&#34;&gt;Preamble&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Richard_Buchta_-_Portrait_of_a_Zande_witchdoctor.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/0a/Richard_Buchta_-_Portrait_of_a_Zande_witchdoctor.jpg/300px-Richard_Buchta_-_Portrait_of_a_Zande_witchdoctor.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Richard Buchta - Portrait of a Zande witchdoctor&#34; title=&#34;Richard Buchta - Portrait of a Zande witchdoctor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am an old atheist and a new agnostic. I don’t &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belief_in_God&#34; title=&#34;Belief in God&#34;&gt;believe in God&lt;/a&gt; in the old-fashioned Russellian way – if I don’t believe in Krishna, Zeus, water sprites or the little teapot orbiting the Sun, I don’t believe in God and the associated supernatual phenomena (monotheism my foot!). However, I am agnostic about nearly everything else and everything else in the new atheist way is pretty much science and reason. If history is any judge (and it is) most of what we believe to be scientific truths today is bunk. This makes me feel not superior at all to people of faith. Sure I think what they believe is a stupid and irrational thing to believe, but I don’t think they are stupid or irrational people to believe it. The smartest people believe the most preposterous things just look at Newton, Chomsky or Dawkins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life expectancy and the length and value of life: On a historical overimagination</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/life-expectancy-and-the-length-and-value-of-life-on-a-historical-overimagination/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/life-expectancy-and-the-length-and-value-of-life-on-a-historical-overimagination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Russian_male_life_expectancy.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/b/b2/Russian_male_life_expectancy.jpg/300px-Russian_male_life_expectancy.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;History of Russia (1992–present)&#34; title=&#34;History of Russia (1992–present)&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;About 10 years ago, I was looking through a book on populations changes in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_lands&#34; title=&#34;Czech lands&#34;&gt;Czech lands&lt;/a&gt;. It consisted of pretty much just tables of data with little commentary. But I was shocked when I came across the life expectancy charts. But not shocked at how short people’s lives had been but how long. The headline figure of life expectancy in the early 1800s was pretty much on par with expectations (I don’t have the book to hand but it was in the high 30s or low 40s). How sad, I thought. So many people died in their 40s before they could experience life in full. But unlike most of the comparisons reporting life expectancy, this one went beyond the overall average. And it was the additional figures that shocked me. Turns out the extremely short life expectancy only applies right at birth. Once you make it to 10, you have a pretty good chance to make it into your late 50s and at 30, your chances of getting your ‘threescore and ten’ were getting pretty good. The problem is that life expectancy rates at birth only really measure child mortality not the typical lives of adults. You can see from this chart: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0005140.html&#34;&gt;http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0005140.html&lt;/a&gt; that in 1850, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States&#34; title=&#34;United States&#34;&gt;the US&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Life_expectancy&#34; title=&#34;Life expectancy&#34;&gt;life expectancy at birth&lt;/a&gt; was a shocking 38 years. But that does not mean that there were a lot of 38-year-olds around dying. Because if you made it to 10, your life expectancy was 58 years and at 30, it was 64 years. Now these are average numbers so it is possible that for any age cohort, exactly half the people died at the start of it and exactly half died at the end of it. But that was not the case after a certain age. Remember, a population where exactly half the people born die at or near birth (age 0) and exactly half live to be 60 will have the average life expectancy of 30. If you reduce child mortality to 10%, you will have the average life expectancy of 54. If you reduce it to 1%, the average life expectancy will be 59.4 years. Most people still die at sixty but very few die at 1. Massive gains in child mortality reduction will have made no difference to the end of life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why don’t metaphorical hawks kill metaphorical doves?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/why-dont-metaphorical-hawks-kill-metaphorical-doves/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/why-dont-metaphorical-hawks-kill-metaphorical-doves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Houseraidiraqaug2007.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/42/Houseraidiraqaug2007.jpg/300px-Houseraidiraqaug2007.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An Iraqi woman looks on as U.S. Army Soldiers &amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;An Iraqi woman looks on as U.S. Army Soldiers ...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A very common metaphor in the political discourse on war is that of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbidae&#34; title=&#34;Columbidae&#34;&gt;doves&lt;/a&gt; (peaceniks) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawk&#34; title=&#34;Hawk&#34;&gt;hawks&lt;/a&gt; (war-mongers). It has been around at least since the cold war. But it stops at “doves=peaceful” and “hawks=aggressive”. It completely ignores other properties of the animals, e.g. the fact that “hawks hunt and kill doves”. I did a lot of searching a could not find any such extensions of the metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comedian identifies a critical flaw in structuralism: Are distinctive features like leather sleeves</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/comedian-identifies-a-critical-flaw-in-structuralism-are-distinctive-features-like-leather-sleeves/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/comedian-identifies-a-critical-flaw-in-structuralism-are-distinctive-features-like-leather-sleeves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I always thought this little bit by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demetri_Martin&#34; title=&#34;Demetri Martin&#34;&gt;Demetri Martin&lt;/a&gt; highlights a crucial deficiency in any distinctive feature analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Demetri Martin: “I was at a party, and I saw a guy with a leather jacket, and I thought, ‘That’s cool’. Then I saw a guy with a leather vest and I thought, ‘That’s not cool’. It was then that I realized what coolness is all about… leather sleeves.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Is phonology all about leather sleeves?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do science fiction writers dream of fascist dictatorships?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/do-science-fiction-writers-dream-of-fascist-dictatorships/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/do-science-fiction-writers-dream-of-fascist-dictatorships/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Galaxy_Science_Fiction_Jan_1953_front_cover.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/9/98/Galaxy_Science_Fiction_Jan_1953_front_cover.jpg/300px-Galaxy_Science_Fiction_Jan_1953_front_cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;This is the cover to the January 1953 issue of&amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;This is the cover to the January 1953 issue of...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some years ago in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://dominiklukes.net&#34;&gt;book review&lt;/a&gt;, I made an off-the-cuff comment that thriller writers tend to be quite right-wing in their outlook whereas science fiction authors are much more progressive and leftist. This is obviously an undue generalisation (as most of such comments tend to be) but it felt intuitively right. Even then I thought of Michael Chricton as the obvious counterexample – a thirller writer with distinctly liberal leanings – but I couldn’t think of a science fiction writer that would provide the counterexample. I put this down to my lack of comprehensive sci-fi reading and thought nothing more of it. Now, I’m not even sure that the general trend is there or at least that the implications are very straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The brain is a bad metaphor for language</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-brain-is-a-bad-metaphor-for-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-brain-is-a-bad-metaphor-for-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This was intended to be a brief note. Instead it developed into a monster post that took me two weeks of stolen moments to write. It’s very light on non-blog references but they exist. Nevertheless, it is still easy to find a number of oversimplifications,  conflations, and other imperfections below. The general thrust of the argument however remains.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-far-can-you-trust-a-neuroscientist&#34;&gt;How Far Can You Trust a Neuroscientist?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Infant_looking_at_shiny_object.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ab/Infant_looking_at_shiny_object.jpg/300px-Infant_looking_at_shiny_object.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Shiny and colored objects usually attract Infa&amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;Shiny and colored objects usually attract Infa...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The most ridiculous metaphor of education courtesy of an economics professor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-most-ridiculous-metaphor-of-education-courtesy-of-an-economics-professor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-most-ridiculous-metaphor-of-education-courtesy-of-an-economics-professor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Acclaimed academics have policy agendas just like anybody else. And often they let them interfere with a straightforward critical analysis of their output. The monumental capacity for blindness of highly intelligent people  is sometimes staggering. &lt;strong&gt;Metaphors and analogies&lt;/strong&gt; (same thing for metaphor hacking) &lt;strong&gt;make thinkers particularly prone to mis-projection blindness&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/glaeser&#34;&gt;Edward Glaeser&lt;/a&gt;, a Harvard economics prof, is just the latest in the long line of economists and blowhards, who think they have the education system licked by comparing it to some -free market gimmick. They generally reveal that they know or care precious little about the full extent of the processes involved in the market and Glaeser is a shining example of this. His analogy is so preposterous and only needs so little thought to break down, I can’t believe he didn’t take a few minutes to to do it himself. Well, actually, I can believe it. It’s pretty,  neat and seductive. So who cares that it is pure non-sense. Here’s what he said:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Philosophers’ songbook #philbitescomp</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/philosophers-songbook-philbitescomp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/philosophers-songbook-philbitescomp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was so inspired by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#search?q=%23philbitescomp&#34;&gt;#philbitescomp&lt;/a&gt; twitter contest that I wrote a short history of philosophy in tweetable fragments of songs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;*Parmenides’ lament:*I guess it will make a change&lt;br&gt;&#xA;when things stop changing&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heracleitus’ blues:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;I cried you the same river&lt;br&gt;&#xA;thrice&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plato’s polka:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;two steps out of the cave&lt;br&gt;&#xA;and look at what you’re doing&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Descartes’ swan song:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;unbidden unwelcome it counts&lt;br&gt;&#xA;yet for a penny I perish&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bishop Berkeley’s soccer fan chant:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Hey Samuel Johnson&lt;br&gt;&#xA;You’re kicking that rock in my mind&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metaphor is my co-pilot: How the literal and metaphorical rely on the same type of knowledge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/metaphor-is-my-co-pilot-how-the-literal-and-metaphorical-rely-on-the-same-type-of-knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/metaphor-is-my-co-pilot-how-the-literal-and-metaphorical-rely-on-the-same-type-of-knowledge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Thanks” to experimental philosophy, we have a bit more evidence confirming, that what many people think about the special &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epistemology&#34; title=&#34;Epistemology&#34;&gt;epistemological&lt;/a&gt; status of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphor&#34; title=&#34;Metaphor&#34;&gt;metaphor&lt;/a&gt; is bunk. We should also note that Gibbs’ and Glucksberg’s teams have been doing a lot of similar research with the same results since the late 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is how &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joshua_Knobe&#34; title=&#34;Joshua Knobe&#34;&gt;Joshua Knobe&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://experimentalphilosophy.typepad.com/experimental_philosophy/2010/08/what-metaphors-mean.html&#34;&gt;Experimental Philosophy&lt;/a&gt; blog summarized a forthcoming paper by Mark Phelan (&lt;a href=&#34;http://pantheon.yale.edu/~mp622/inadequacy.pdf&#34;&gt;http://pantheon.yale.edu/~mp622/inadequacy.pdf&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In short, it looks like it really is pretty impossible to explain what a metaphor means. But that is not because of anything special about metaphors. It is merely a reflection of the fact that we can’t explain what any sentence means.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://experimentalphilosophy.typepad.com/experimental_philosophy/2010/08/what-metaphors-mean.html&#34;&gt;Experimental Philosophy: What Metaphors Mean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Tortoise and the Hare: Analogy for Academia in the Digital World?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/the-tortoise-and-the-hare-analogy-for-academia-in-the-digital-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/the-tortoise-and-the-hare-analogy-for-academia-in-the-digital-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dancohen.org&#34; title=&#34;Dan Cohen&#34;&gt;Dan Cohen&lt;/a&gt; has decided to “&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crowdsourcing&#34; title=&#34;Crowdsourcing&#34;&gt;crowdsource&lt;/a&gt;” (a fascinating blend, by the way) the title of his next book with the following instructions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The title should be a couplet like “The X and the Y” where X can be “Highbrow Humanities” “Elite Academia” “The Ivory Tower” “Deep/High Thought” [insert your idea] and Y can be “Lowbrow Web” “Common Web” “Vernacular Technology/Web” “Public Web” [insert your idea]. so possible titles are “The Highbrow Humanities and the Lowbrow Web” or “The Ivory Tower and the Wild Web” etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Chomsky doesn’t count as a gifted linguist</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/why-chomsky-doesnt-count-as-a-gifted-linguist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/why-chomsky-doesnt-count-as-a-gifted-linguist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Somebody commented on the Language Log saying “of course […] Chomsky was a massively gifted linguist” &lt;a href=&#34;http://j.mp/9Q98Bx&#34;&gt;http://j.mp/9Q98Bx&lt;/a&gt; and for some reason, to use a Czech idiom, the handle of the jar repeatedly used to fetch water just fell off. Meaning, I’ve had enough.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think we should stop thinking of Chomsky as a gifted linguist. He was certainly a gifted mathematician and logician still is a gifted orator and analyst of political discourse (sometimes putting professionals in this area to shame). But I honestly cannot think of a single insight he’s had about how language works as language. His main contribution to the study of language (his only one really) was a description of how certain combinatorial properties of English syntax can be modeled using a particular formal system.  This was a valuable insight but as has been repeatedly documented (e.g. Newmeyer 1986) its runaway success was due to a particular historical context and was later fed by the political prominence of its originator. Unfortunately, everything that followed was predicated on the model being isomorphic with the thing modeled. Meaning all subsequent insights of Chomsky and his followers were confined to refining the model in response to what other people knew about language and not once that I can think of using it to elucidate an actual linguistic phenomenon. (Well, I tell lie here, James MacCawley who worked with GB – and there must have been others – was probably an exception.) Chomsky’s followers who actually continued to have real insights about language – Ross,  Langacker, Lakoff, Fillmore – simply ceased to work within that field – their frustration given voice here by Robin Tolmach Lakoff:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why ideas aren’t enough to solve the Palestine-Israeli conflict</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/why-ideas-arent-enough-to-solve-the-palestine-israeli-conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/why-ideas-arent-enough-to-solve-the-palestine-israeli-conflict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2010-07/23/crowdsource-israeli-palestinian-conflict&#34;&gt;advertising agency is trying to solve a bloody conflict&lt;/a&gt;. This is presumptuous on such as scale that it could be called idiotic. Quoth &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theimpossiblebrief.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.theimpossiblebrief.com&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Rather than ‘out of date’ policies, we need ‘out of the box’ solutions. Let’s show the world that creative minds at their best can inspire even political leaders.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Assuming that there’s an idea out there about resolving this conflict that noone’s ever thought of is nonsense. We should call this assumption that simple ideas can solve difficult problems the “TED Syndrome” (btw: I love TED talks, even if I share &lt;a href=&#34;http://halfanhour.blogspot.com/2010/02/ted-is-political.html&#34;&gt;Stephen Downes’ misgivings&lt;/a&gt; about the TED ‘elite’). Simple solutions to complex problems exist but they are very rare and when we hear about them, we are seldom told the whole story. Generally, it should be safe to assume that a solution should be of proportional complexity to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I write like… a new more sophisticated stripper name?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/i-write-like-a-new-more-sophisticated-stripper-name/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/i-write-like-a-new-more-sophisticated-stripper-name/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Making connections between ourselves and other people no matter how arbitrary, is an incredibly popular communal as well as private activity. The many algorithms for generating one’s stripper, mobster or some other kind of name have graduated from napkins in bars to Facebook apps and now proper quantitative analysis of text samples. But deep down they’re still the same. Is there a space here for hacking? Can we take this natural tendency, take it apart and put it back together again? Use it for good or for ill? I suppose most social engineering is the hacking of propositional frames, but are there explicit hacks of figurative language and thought? It’s certainly powerful enough when you find out that based on the About page here:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What it’s not about so much about</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/what-its-not-about-so-much-about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/what-its-not-about-so-much-about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Enter your email address to subscribe to this blog and receive notifications of new posts by email.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hacking a metaphor in five steps</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/hacking-a-metaphor-in-five-steps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/hacking-a-metaphor-in-five-steps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;preliminaries&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preliminaries&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.&lt;/strong&gt; Before you start &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphor&#34; title=&#34;Metaphor&#34;&gt;metaphor&lt;/a&gt; hacking you must first accept that you don’t have a choice but to speak in some sort of a figurative fashion. Almost nothing worth saying is entirely literal and there are many things whose “literalness” is rooted in metaphor. Look at “I sat in a chair the whole day.” Looks very literal at first glance but it depends on our understanding of a chair as a container (e.g. he was spilling out of his chair) and the day as an object (e.g. she was counting the days, cutting the day short, a long day, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What it’s all About</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/what-its-all-about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2010/what-its-all-about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphor&#34; title=&#34;Metaphor&#34;&gt;Metaphors&lt;/a&gt; are not just something extra we use when we’re feeling poetic or at a loss for le mot juste, they are all over our minds, texts and conversations. Just like conjunctions, tenses or word. And just like anything else, they can be used for good or ill, on purpose or without conscious regard. Their meanings can be exposed, explored and exorcised. They can be brought from the dead by fresh perspectives or trodden into the ground by frequent use. They may bring us into the very heights of ecstasy or they may pass by unnoticed. They elluminate and obscure, lead and mislead, bring life and death. They can be too constrained or they can taken too far. They can be wrong and they can be right. And they can be hacked.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
