<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2013s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2013s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Binders full of women with mighty pens: What is metonymy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/binders-full-of-women-with-mighty-pens-what-is-metonymy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/binders-full-of-women-with-mighty-pens-what-is-metonymy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Metonymy in the wild&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://25.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_md37c5dYtG1rj8amio1_1280.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://25.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_md37c5dYtG1rj8amio1_1280.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Things were not going well for Mitt Romney in early autumn of last year. And then he responded to a query about gender equality with this sentence:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I had the chance to pull together a cabinet, and all the applicants seemed to be men… I went to a number of women’s groups and said, ‘Can you help us find folks?’ and they brought us whole binders full of women.” &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binders&#34;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binders&lt;/a&gt;_full_of_women&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three books of the year 2013 and some books of the century 1900-2013</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/three-books-of-the-year-2013-and-some-books-of-the-century-1900-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/three-books-of-the-year-2013-and-some-books-of-the-century-1900-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been asked (as every year) to nominate three books of the year for Lidové Noviny (a Czech paper I contribute to occasionally). This is always a tough choice for me and some years I don’t even bother responding. This is because I don’t tend to read books ‘of the moment’ and range widely in my reading across time periods. But I think I have some good ones this time. Additionally, Lidové Noviny are celebrating 120 years of being a major Czech newspaper so they also asked me for a book of the century (since 1900 till now). It makes no sense to even try to pick ‘the one’, so I picked three categories that are of interest to me (language, society and fiction) and chose three books in each.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pervasiveness of Obliging Metaphors in Thought and Deed</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/pervasiveness-of-obliging-metaphors-in-thought-and-deed/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/pervasiveness-of-obliging-metaphors-in-thought-and-deed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“when history is at its most obliging, the history-writer needs be at his most wary.” (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/China-History-John-Keay/dp/0007221789&#34;&gt;China by John Keay&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/16230215@N08/6220425549/&#34; title=&#34;Die Mykologen - Glückspilze - Lucky Fellows - Fungi Experts&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6166/6220425549_cc19140a63.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Die Mykologen - Glückspilze - Lucky Fellows - Fungi Experts&#34; title=&#34;Die Mykologen - Glückspilze - Lucky Fellows - Fungi Experts&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I came across this nugget of wisdom when I was re-reading the Introduction to John Keay’s history of China. And it struck me that in some way this quote could be a part of the motto of this blog. The whole thing might then read something like this:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Storms in all Teacups: The Power and Inequality in the Battle for Science Universality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/storms-in-all-teacups-the-power-and-inequality-in-the-battle-for-science-universality/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/storms-in-all-teacups-the-power-and-inequality-in-the-battle-for-science-universality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The great blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://genealogyreligion.net/salubrious-storm&#34;&gt;Genealogy of Religion&lt;/a&gt; posted this video with a somewhat approving commentary:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The video started off with panache and promised some entertainment, however, I found myself increasingly annoyed as the video continued. The problem is that this is an exchange of cliches that pretends to be a fight of truth against ignorance. Sure, Storm doesn’t put forward a very coherent argument for her position, but neither does Minchin. His description of science vs. faith is laughable (being in awe at the size of the universe, my foot) and nowhere does he display any nuance nor, frankly, any evidence that he is doing anything other than parroting what he’s heard on some TV interview with Dawkins. I have much more sympathy with the Storms of this world than these self-styled defenders of science whose only credentials are that they can remember a bit of high school physics or chemistry and have read an article by some neo-atheist in Wired. What’s worse, it’s would be rationalists like him who do what passes for science reporting in major newspapers or on the BBC.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How we use metaphors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/how-we-use-metaphors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/how-we-use-metaphors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was reminded by &lt;a href=&#34;http://thelousylinguist.blogspot.co.uk/2013/04/the-birth-of-metaphor.html&#34;&gt;this blog post on LousyLinguist&lt;/a&gt; that many people still see metaphor as an unproblematic homogeneous concept leading to much circular thinking about them.  I wrote about that quite a few years ago in:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lukeš, D., 2005. Towards a classification of metaphor use in text: Issues in conceptual discourse analysis of a domain-specific corpus. In &lt;em&gt;Third Workshop on Corpus-Based Approaches to Figurative Language&lt;/em&gt;. Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I suggested that a classification of metaphor had better focused on their use rather than inherent nature. I came up with the heuristic device of: cognitive, social and textual uses of metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do we need a gaming literacy: Literacy metaphor hack</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/do-we-need-a-gaming-literacy-literacy-metaphor-hack/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/do-we-need-a-gaming-literacy-literacy-metaphor-hack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-am-a-gaming-semi-literate&#34;&gt;I am a gaming semi-literate!&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was listening to the discussion of the latest BioShock game on &lt;a href=&#34;http://twit.tv/show/this-week-in-tech/399&#34;&gt;the latest TWiT podcast&lt;/a&gt; when I realized that I am in fact game illiterate. I am hearing these stories and descriptions of experiences but I know I can’t access them directly without a major investment in knowledge and skill acquisition. So, this is what people with no or limited literacy must feel like in highly literacy-dependent environments. I really want to access the stories in the way they are told by the game. But I know I can’t. I will stumble, be discouraged, not have a very good time before I can have a good time. I will be a struggling gamer, in the same way that there are struggling readers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Framing and constructions as a bridge between cognition and culture: Two Abstracts for Cognitive Futures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/framing-and-constructions-as-a-bridge-between-cognition-and-culture-two-abstracts-for-cognitive-futures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2013/framing-and-constructions-as-a-bridge-between-cognition-and-culture-two-abstracts-for-cognitive-futures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just found out that both abstracts I submitted to the Cognitive Futures of the Humanities Conference were accepted. I was really only expecting one to get through but I’m looking forward to talking about the ideas in both.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first first talk has foundations in a paper I wrote almost 5 years ago now about the nature of evidence for discourse. But the idea is pretty much central to all my thinking on the subject of culture and cognition. The challenge as I see it is to come up with a cognitively realistic but not a cognitively reductionist account of culture. And the problem I see is that often the learning only goes one way. The people studying culture are supposed to be learning about the results of research on cognition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
