<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2011s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2011s on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Moral Compass Metaphor Points to Surprising Places</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/moral-compass-metaphor-points-to-surprising-places/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/moral-compass-metaphor-points-to-surprising-places/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I thought the moral compass metaphor has mostly left current political discourse but it just cropped up – this time pointing from left to right – as [David Plouffe accused Mitt Romney of not having one]((&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/political-animal/2011_10/no_core033193.php)&#34;&gt;http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/political-animal/2011_10/no_core033193.php)&lt;/a&gt;. As I keep repeating, George Lakoff once said “Metaphors can kill.” And Moral Compass has certainly done its share of homicidal damage. Justifying wars, interventions and unflinching black and white resolve in the face of gray circumstances. It is a killer metaphor!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Killer App is a bad metaphor for historical trends, good for pseudoteaching</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/killer-app-is-a-bad-metaphor-for-historical-trends-good-for-pseudoteaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/killer-app-is-a-bad-metaphor-for-historical-trends-good-for-pseudoteaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Latin_alphabet_world_distribution.svg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/f/f4/Latin_alphabet_world_distribution.svg/300px-Latin_alphabet_world_distribution.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;This map shows the countries in the world that&amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;This map shows the countries in the world that...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niall_Ferguson&#34; title=&#34;Niall Ferguson&#34;&gt;Niall Ferguson&lt;/a&gt; wrote in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/education/2011/mar/29/history-school-crisis-disconnected-events&#34;&gt;The Guardian some time ago&lt;/a&gt; about how awful history education has become with these “new-fangled” 40-year-old methods like focusing on “history skills” that leads to kids leaving school knowing “unconnected fragments of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_world&#34; title=&#34;Western world&#34;&gt;Western history&lt;/a&gt;: Henry VIII and Hitler, with a small dose of Martin Luther King, Jr.” but not who was the reigning English monarch at the time of the Armada. Instead, he wants history to be taught his way: deep trends leading to the understanding why the “West” rules and why Fergusson is the cleverest of all the historians that ever lived. He even provided (and how cute is this) a lesson plan!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Language learning in literature as a source domain for generative metaphors about anything</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/language-learning-in-literature-as-a-source-domain-for-generative-metaphors-about-anything/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/language-learning-in-literature-as-a-source-domain-for-generative-metaphors-about-anything/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Minamoto_no_Yoritomo.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/76/Minamoto_no_Yoritomo.jpg/300px-Minamoto_no_Yoritomo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Portrait of Yoritomo, copy of the 1179 origina&amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;Portrait of Yoritomo, copy of the 1179 origina...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my thinking about things human, I often like to draw on the domain of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_language_acquisition&#34; title=&#34;Second language acquisition&#34;&gt;second language learning&lt;/a&gt; as the source of analogies. The problem is that relatively few people in the English speaking world have experience with language learning to such an extent that they can actually map things onto it. In fact, in my experience, even people who have a lot of experience with language learning are actually not aware of all the things that were happening while they were learning. And of course awareness of research or language learning theories is not to be expected. This is not helped by the language teaching profession’s propaganda that language learning is “fun” and “rewarding” (whatever that is). In fact my mantra of language learning (I learned from my friend Bill Perry) is that “language learning is hard and takes time” – at least if you expect to achieve a level of competence above that of “impressing the natives” with your “please” and “thank you”. In that, language learning is like any other human endeavor but because of its relatively bounded nature — when compared to, for instance, culture — it can be particularly illuminating.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The natural logistics of life: The Internet really changes almost nothing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-natural-logistics-of-life-the-internet-really-changes-almost-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-natural-logistics-of-life-the-internet-really-changes-almost-nothing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Youve-Got-Mail-Tom-Hanks/dp/6305368171%3FSubscriptionId%3D0G81C5DAZ03ZR9WH9X82%26tag%3Dzemanta-20%26linkCode%3Dxm2%26camp%3D2025%26creative%3D165953%26creativeASIN%3D6305368171&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51JN65AE3YL._SL300_.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cover of &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;ve Got Mail&amp;rdquo;&#34; title=&#34;Cover of &amp;quot;You&#39;ve Got Mail&amp;quot;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cover of You&amp;rsquo;ve Got Mail&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a post that has been germinating for a long time. But it was most immediately inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshall_Poe&#34; title=&#34;Marshall Poe&#34;&gt;Marshall Poe&lt;/a&gt;‘s article claiming that “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hnn.us/articles/133910.html&#34;&gt;The Internet Changes Nothing&lt;/a&gt;“. And as it turns out, I mostly agree.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OK, this may sound a bit paradoxical. Twelve years ago, when I submitted my first column to be published, I delivered the text to my editor on a diskette. Now, I don’t even have an editor (or at least not for this kind of writing). I just click a button and my text is published. But! If my server logs are to be trusted, it will be read by 10s or at best 100s of people over its lifetime. That’s more than if I’d just written some notes to myself or published it in an academic journal but much less than if I publish it in a national daily with a readership of hundreds of thousands. Not all of them will read what I write but more than would on this blog.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;So while democratising the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Publishing&#34; title=&#34;Publishing&#34;&gt;publishing industry&lt;/a&gt; has worked for Kos, Huffington and many others, still many more blogs languish in obscurity. I can say anything I want but my voice matters little in the cacophony.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When is subtle manipulation of data a flat out lie? Truth about Chinese prisons [UPDATE]</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/when-is-subtle-manipulation-of-data-a-flat-out-lie-truth-about-chinese-prisons-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/when-is-subtle-manipulation-of-data-a-flat-out-lie-truth-about-chinese-prisons-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/China&#34; title=&#34;China&#34;&gt;China&lt;/a&gt; kick lately (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/China-History-John-Keay/dp/0007221789/&#34;&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chinahistorypodcast.com&#34;&gt;listening&lt;/a&gt; about its history and global position) and a crime public policy kick (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/When-Brute-Force-Fails-Punishment/dp/0691148643&#34;&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcast.oid.ucla.edu/courses/2009-2010/2010winter/pp10a-1/podcast.xml&#34;&gt;listening&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_A.R._Kleiman&#34; title=&#34;Mark A.R. Kleiman&#34;&gt;Mark Kleiman&lt;/a&gt;). I was struck when I heard Mark say in an interview that the US has more people in jail in absolute terms than China. So I went about to looking for some data. I found the most comprehensive source of info in the “&lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;amp;q=cache:lzGQNLGCeZ0J:www.kcl.ac.uk/depsta/law/research/icps/downloads/world-prison-pop-seventh.pdf+chinese+prison+population&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;gl=uk&amp;amp;pid=bl&amp;amp;srcid=ADGEESi8tLqSmM3bovvLsczZmFxd77uSek8aIbQTiiWsO14Y9ea0iMrb1RVVoclUbZ9wWTZq4i4f5XQwew_ehsS63rnVYyAG8yodlBOluLcRY3heNMf1jYkvOKpD--2NOypl1P30vuUC&amp;amp;sig=AHIEtbScQOPaOogNCd2X81PAVQhcUMRI9Q&#34;&gt;World Prison Population List&lt;/a&gt;” published by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://maps.google.com/maps?ll=51.5119444444,-0.116111111111&amp;amp;spn=0.01,0.01&amp;amp;q=51.5119444444,-0.116111111111%20(King%27s%20College%20London)&amp;amp;t=h&#34; title=&#34;King&#39;s College London&#34;&gt;King’s College London&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Centre_for_Prison_Studies&#34; title=&#34;International Centre for Prison Studies&#34;&gt;International Centre for Prison Studies&lt;/a&gt;. Their top bullet point is alarming:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I object: A male feminist’s view on the Duchess of Cambridge’s Wedding dress</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/i-object-a-male-feminists-view-on-the-duchess-of-cambridges-wedding-dress/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/i-object-a-male-feminists-view-on-the-duchess-of-cambridges-wedding-dress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/16061323@N07/5664356426&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5144/5664356426_e656ccff2a_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Welcome to our wedding&#34; title=&#34;Welcome to our wedding&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image by bobfranklin (mostly tacit) via Flickr&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Maybe I should be watching more TV but I honestly had no idea what &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kate_Middleton&#34; title=&#34;Kate Middleton&#34;&gt;Kate Middleton&lt;/a&gt; looked like. There must have been times I would have heard references to her and thought she was some kind of actress or model. And frankly, I still don’t care.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But I do care about her dress. I am quite naive in the way of things (despite my interest in the ethnography of the everyday) so the fact that it may matter what the future queen will be wearing on her wedding day was not obvious to me. And matter more to many than whether a former prime minister or two were invited. I heard about it on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/today/&#34; title=&#34;Today (BBC Radio 4)&#34;&gt;Today programme&lt;/a&gt; this morning and realised that I had been pretty silly not to have thought about it and then all was clear when I got a text from a female friend who professed that the dress was the main thing of import.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poetry without metaphor? Sure but can it darn your socks?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/poetry-without-metaphor-sure-but-can-it-darn-your-socks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/poetry-without-metaphor-sure-but-can-it-darn-your-socks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:LiBai.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4c/LiBai.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Chinese poet Li Bai from the Tang dynasty, in &amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;Chinese poet Li Bai from the Tang dynasty, in ...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://languagelog.ldc.upenn.edu/nll/?p=3108&#34; title=&#34;Language Log&#34;&gt;Language Log&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_H._Mair&#34; title=&#34;Victor H. Mair&#34;&gt;Victor Mair&lt;/a&gt; puts to rest that all English expressions have to be tensed and thus prevent timeless poetry. He shares his translation of a 13th century &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Chinese_language_poets&#34; title=&#34;List of Chinese language poets&#34;&gt;Chinese poet&lt;/a&gt; thus:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Autumn Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ma_Zhiyuan&#34;&gt;Ma Zhiyuan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Withered wisteria, old tree, darkling crows –&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Little bridge over flowing water by someone’s house –&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Emaciated horse on an ancient road in the western wind –&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Evening sun setting in the west –&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Broken-hearted man on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Religion, if it exists, is negotiation of underdetermined metaphoric cognition [UPDATED]</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/religion-if-it-exists-is-negotiation-of-underdetermined-metaphoric-cognition-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/religion-if-it-exists-is-negotiation-of-underdetermined-metaphoric-cognition-updated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;preamble&#34;&gt;Preamble&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Richard_Buchta_-_Portrait_of_a_Zande_witchdoctor.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/0a/Richard_Buchta_-_Portrait_of_a_Zande_witchdoctor.jpg/300px-Richard_Buchta_-_Portrait_of_a_Zande_witchdoctor.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Richard Buchta - Portrait of a Zande witchdoctor&#34; title=&#34;Richard Buchta - Portrait of a Zande witchdoctor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am an old atheist and a new agnostic. I don’t &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belief_in_God&#34; title=&#34;Belief in God&#34;&gt;believe in God&lt;/a&gt; in the old-fashioned Russellian way – if I don’t believe in Krishna, Zeus, water sprites or the little teapot orbiting the Sun, I don’t believe in God and the associated supernatual phenomena (monotheism my foot!). However, I am agnostic about nearly everything else and everything else in the new atheist way is pretty much science and reason. If history is any judge (and it is) most of what we believe to be scientific truths today is bunk. This makes me feel not superior at all to people of faith. Sure I think what they believe is a stupid and irrational thing to believe, but I don’t think they are stupid or irrational people to believe it. The smartest people believe the most preposterous things just look at Newton, Chomsky or Dawkins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life expectancy and the length and value of life: On a historical overimagination</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/life-expectancy-and-the-length-and-value-of-life-on-a-historical-overimagination/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/life-expectancy-and-the-length-and-value-of-life-on-a-historical-overimagination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Russian_male_life_expectancy.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/b/b2/Russian_male_life_expectancy.jpg/300px-Russian_male_life_expectancy.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;History of Russia (1992–present)&#34; title=&#34;History of Russia (1992–present)&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;About 10 years ago, I was looking through a book on populations changes in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_lands&#34; title=&#34;Czech lands&#34;&gt;Czech lands&lt;/a&gt;. It consisted of pretty much just tables of data with little commentary. But I was shocked when I came across the life expectancy charts. But not shocked at how short people’s lives had been but how long. The headline figure of life expectancy in the early 1800s was pretty much on par with expectations (I don’t have the book to hand but it was in the high 30s or low 40s). How sad, I thought. So many people died in their 40s before they could experience life in full. But unlike most of the comparisons reporting life expectancy, this one went beyond the overall average. And it was the additional figures that shocked me. Turns out the extremely short life expectancy only applies right at birth. Once you make it to 10, you have a pretty good chance to make it into your late 50s and at 30, your chances of getting your ‘threescore and ten’ were getting pretty good. The problem is that life expectancy rates at birth only really measure child mortality not the typical lives of adults. You can see from this chart: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0005140.html&#34;&gt;http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0005140.html&lt;/a&gt; that in 1850, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States&#34; title=&#34;United States&#34;&gt;the US&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Life_expectancy&#34; title=&#34;Life expectancy&#34;&gt;life expectancy at birth&lt;/a&gt; was a shocking 38 years. But that does not mean that there were a lot of 38-year-olds around dying. Because if you made it to 10, your life expectancy was 58 years and at 30, it was 64 years. Now these are average numbers so it is possible that for any age cohort, exactly half the people died at the start of it and exactly half died at the end of it. But that was not the case after a certain age. Remember, a population where exactly half the people born die at or near birth (age 0) and exactly half live to be 60 will have the average life expectancy of 30. If you reduce child mortality to 10%, you will have the average life expectancy of 54. If you reduce it to 1%, the average life expectancy will be 59.4 years. Most people still die at sixty but very few die at 1. Massive gains in child mortality reduction will have made no difference to the end of life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why don’t metaphorical hawks kill metaphorical doves?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/why-dont-metaphorical-hawks-kill-metaphorical-doves/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/why-dont-metaphorical-hawks-kill-metaphorical-doves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Houseraidiraqaug2007.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/42/Houseraidiraqaug2007.jpg/300px-Houseraidiraqaug2007.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An Iraqi woman looks on as U.S. Army Soldiers &amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;An Iraqi woman looks on as U.S. Army Soldiers ...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A very common metaphor in the political discourse on war is that of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbidae&#34; title=&#34;Columbidae&#34;&gt;doves&lt;/a&gt; (peaceniks) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawk&#34; title=&#34;Hawk&#34;&gt;hawks&lt;/a&gt; (war-mongers). It has been around at least since the cold war. But it stops at “doves=peaceful” and “hawks=aggressive”. It completely ignores other properties of the animals, e.g. the fact that “hawks hunt and kill doves”. I did a lot of searching a could not find any such extensions of the metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comedian identifies a critical flaw in structuralism: Are distinctive features like leather sleeves</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/comedian-identifies-a-critical-flaw-in-structuralism-are-distinctive-features-like-leather-sleeves/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/comedian-identifies-a-critical-flaw-in-structuralism-are-distinctive-features-like-leather-sleeves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I always thought this little bit by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demetri_Martin&#34; title=&#34;Demetri Martin&#34;&gt;Demetri Martin&lt;/a&gt; highlights a crucial deficiency in any distinctive feature analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Demetri Martin: “I was at a party, and I saw a guy with a leather jacket, and I thought, ‘That’s cool’. Then I saw a guy with a leather vest and I thought, ‘That’s not cool’. It was then that I realized what coolness is all about… leather sleeves.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Is phonology all about leather sleeves?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do science fiction writers dream of fascist dictatorships?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/do-science-fiction-writers-dream-of-fascist-dictatorships/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/do-science-fiction-writers-dream-of-fascist-dictatorships/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Galaxy_Science_Fiction_Jan_1953_front_cover.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/9/98/Galaxy_Science_Fiction_Jan_1953_front_cover.jpg/300px-Galaxy_Science_Fiction_Jan_1953_front_cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;This is the cover to the January 1953 issue of&amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;This is the cover to the January 1953 issue of...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Image via Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some years ago in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://dominiklukes.net&#34;&gt;book review&lt;/a&gt;, I made an off-the-cuff comment that thriller writers tend to be quite right-wing in their outlook whereas science fiction authors are much more progressive and leftist. This is obviously an undue generalisation (as most of such comments tend to be) but it felt intuitively right. Even then I thought of Michael Chricton as the obvious counterexample – a thirller writer with distinctly liberal leanings – but I couldn’t think of a science fiction writer that would provide the counterexample. I put this down to my lack of comprehensive sci-fi reading and thought nothing more of it. Now, I’m not even sure that the general trend is there or at least that the implications are very straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The brain is a bad metaphor for language</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-brain-is-a-bad-metaphor-for-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-brain-is-a-bad-metaphor-for-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This was intended to be a brief note. Instead it developed into a monster post that took me two weeks of stolen moments to write. It’s very light on non-blog references but they exist. Nevertheless, it is still easy to find a number of oversimplifications,  conflations, and other imperfections below. The general thrust of the argument however remains.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-far-can-you-trust-a-neuroscientist&#34;&gt;How Far Can You Trust a Neuroscientist?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Infant_looking_at_shiny_object.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ab/Infant_looking_at_shiny_object.jpg/300px-Infant_looking_at_shiny_object.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Shiny and colored objects usually attract Infa&amp;hellip;&#34; title=&#34;Shiny and colored objects usually attract Infa...&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The most ridiculous metaphor of education courtesy of an economics professor</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-most-ridiculous-metaphor-of-education-courtesy-of-an-economics-professor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2011/the-most-ridiculous-metaphor-of-education-courtesy-of-an-economics-professor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Acclaimed academics have policy agendas just like anybody else. And often they let them interfere with a straightforward critical analysis of their output. The monumental capacity for blindness of highly intelligent people  is sometimes staggering. &lt;strong&gt;Metaphors and analogies&lt;/strong&gt; (same thing for metaphor hacking) &lt;strong&gt;make thinkers particularly prone to mis-projection blindness&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/glaeser&#34;&gt;Edward Glaeser&lt;/a&gt;, a Harvard economics prof, is just the latest in the long line of economists and blowhards, who think they have the education system licked by comparing it to some -free market gimmick. They generally reveal that they know or care precious little about the full extent of the processes involved in the market and Glaeser is a shining example of this. His analogy is so preposterous and only needs so little thought to break down, I can’t believe he didn’t take a few minutes to to do it himself. Well, actually, I can believe it. It’s pretty,  neat and seductive. So who cares that it is pure non-sense. Here’s what he said:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
