<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linguistics on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/tags/linguistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linguistics on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/tags/linguistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>17 Things Everyone Should Know About Language But Doesn’t Even Know to Ask</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/17-things-everyone-should-know-about-language-but-doesnt-even-know-to-ask/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/17-things-everyone-should-know-about-language-but-doesnt-even-know-to-ask/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Languages are not a simple matter of grammar. Any language policy must consider what is known about language from the fields of pragmatics, sociolinguistics, and cognitive linguistics. Here I collected, 17 key findings about language from across many fields of linguistic inquiry. These are descriptive things we know with some certainty about how language works.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Who should know these things? Everyone would be a nice thing but in the absence of that, I’d settle for some of these: Teachers and especially language teachers. Journalists. Language policy experts. And (and here we’re just praying for a miracle) grammar mavens.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fruit loops and metaphors: Metaphors are not about explaining the abstract through concrete but…</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-throug/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-throug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;fruit-loops-and-metaphors-metaphors-are-not-about-explaining-the-abstract-through-concrete-but-about-the-dynamic-process-of-negotiated-sensemaking&#34;&gt;Fruit loops and metaphors: Metaphors are not about explaining the abstract through concrete but about the dynamic process of negotiated sensemaking&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/960/1*_T0MTlgi3p0CjzWNmCYDIg.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the less fortunate consequences of the popularity of the conceptual metaphor paradigm (which is also the one I by and large work with) is the highlighting of the embodied metaphor at the expenses of others. This gives the impression that metaphors are there to explain more abstract concepts in terms of more concrete ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
