<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Music on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/tags/music/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Music on Dominik Lukeš — Writing Corpus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/tags/music/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>10 ways in which music is like language and 8 (more important) ways in which it is not</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/10-ways-in-which-music-is-like-language-and-8-more-important-ways-in-which-it-is/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/dominiklukes-llmstxt/2018/10-ways-in-which-music-is-like-language-and-8-more-important-ways-in-which-it-is/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People often talk about music as if it were language. Leonard Bernstein even recorded a series of lectures applying &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MB7ZOdp__gQ&#34;&gt;Chomsky’s theory of generative grammar to music&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kojvij-PNq8&#34;&gt;Chomsky himself&lt;/a&gt; answered a question on this in a not very satisfying manner. Some people can get very exercised over this.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But it seems to me that a playing around with strengths and weakness of the music = language metaphor can help us come to grips with the question a bit better. We can find a number of mappings between music and language but an equal number of mis-mappings. We do not need to go very far into it to see where they are. That does not mean that a deeper investigation into musical properties of language and linguistic properties of music cannot be fruitful. And obviously they are both universal human faculties — but looking for a musical essence in language or a linguistic essence in music is what a metaphor aware approach to this question is hoping to warn against.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
